<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The prentises practise in Godlinesse, and his true freedome Diuided into ten chapters. Written by B.P.</title>
            <author>B. P., fl. 1608.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 196 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 105 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08772</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19057</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120852</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856045</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856045</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21561</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08772)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21561)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1324:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The prentises practise in Godlinesse, and his true freedome Diuided into ten chapters. Written by B.P.</title>
                  <author>B. P., fl. 1608.</author>
                  <author>T. R., fl. 1608.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[15], 71, [14] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes, for Iohn Bach, and are to be sold at his shop in Popes head Palace,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: T.R.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Protestant authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21561:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21561:1"/>
            <p>THE PRENTISES PRACTISE IN GODLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and his true freedome. Diuided into ten Chapters. Written by B. P.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROVERBS 17.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>A diſcreet Seruant ſhall haue more rule then the Sonnes that haue no wiſedome, and ſhall haue like heritage with the Brethren.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device. Framed device of a fleur-de-lis with In Domino confido. McKerrow number 269.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes,</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bach,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in Popes head Palace. 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21561:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21561:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RELIGIOVS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſed and vertuous yong men, the Apprentiſes of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of London, all happines both in this life and in the life to come.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ythagoras</hi> the Philoſopher expreſſing the double courſe of mans life by the letter Y, intimateth that which our Sauiour Chriſt hath more plainly ſet downe concerning the double way; whereof one hath a ſtrait paſſage and narrow gate at the firſt, which few do embrace; but in the end thereof, there is great comfort and reſt, for it gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the paſſenger vnto eternall happineſſe and ſaluation: The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is wide and ſpacious at the
<pb facs="tcp:21561:3"/> beginning, wherby many trauaile, but in the end they find great trouble and ſtraitneſſe, for it leadeth vnto euerlaſting woe and deſtruction. Both theſe waies are ſet before our eies as life and death; for we may not be idle, but of neceſſity muſt walke, ſeeing our life is a pilgrimage, and chooſe either to trauell the narrow way vnto life, or to runne the broad way vnto death. The way of life, is a religious profeſſion, a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and conſcionable carriage, when wee giue vnto God, that which is Gods; and to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> our Magiſtrates and Maſters, that which belongeth vnto them. The gate of this way is narrow, and the paſſage ſtrait: for the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of fleſh and blood muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, our affections bridled, and the whole man captiuated vnder the yoke of the obedience
<pb facs="tcp:21561:3"/> of Ieſus Chriſt, as alſo ſuch whom we are to obey &amp; ſerue vnder him. The way of death, is a ſinfull and licentious life, when we ſerue ſin and Satan, and make no conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce neither towards god not man. The gate of this way in the beginning is broad, and the paſſage eaſie, giuing liberty &amp; full head to our youthy affections and luſts of the fleſh, but the end is vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter perdition and ſtraitnes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let euery yong man, behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding theſe two waies, chooſe that which leadeth vnto eternall life in heauen, by a ſanctified life for a time on earth, walking ſincerely with him who is the <hi>Way,</hi> the <hi>Truth</hi> and the <hi>Life.</hi> To this end I haue penned this inſuing. Tractate, which, welbeloued Brethren, I haue commended vnto your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable acceptance, that therin you might ſee which is the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb facs="tcp:21561:4"/> way, the way of life, &amp; learne how to trauell therein, neither let that diuelliſh prouerb, <hi>a yong Saint an old Diuel,</hi> direct your courſe, but endeuor being yong to be Saints of God, &amp; to dedicate your youth to him and his ſeruice onely, who vndoubtedly will giue you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie to perſeuere, that you may become <hi>Old Saints</hi> on earth, and at laſt a ioyfull end, that you may be <hi>Bleſſed Saints</hi> in heauen, &amp; liue with him for euermore: to whoſe gracious &amp; mercifull protection, in the meane time I commend you all. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your euer louing Brother, <hi>B. P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21561:4"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian and Charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reader, many are the diſcourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts that the children of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue at the hands of wicked men, in this iron and declining age of the world, from the ſincere embracing of the Goſpell, or ſhewing forth the fruits of ſanctification, in this croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and ſinfull generation, but much more from publiſhing any holy Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, tending to this purpoſe: to omit the bookes that are written, not of vertue and verity, but of vilenes and vanity, which many offer now a daies, as ſo many Sacrifices to the diuell (by the which as with ſo many cups of poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he infecteth the hearts of millio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of
<pb facs="tcp:21561:5"/> people) what great delight the enemy of mankind taketh herein, he that can ſee any thing, may eaſily diſcerne by the curſed inſtruments which he raiſeth vp from time to time; as his children the Papiſts, whom wee had thought (long agen) had beene dead in their neſts, yet now like ſerpents hauing cast their coates, begin to lift vp their heads out of their holes wi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th freſh and new coloured hereſie, and with their poyſoned pennes (as a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man of God ſaith) haue defiled not inke and paper, but heauen and earth with their deteſtable and ſatanicall wickedneſſe. But to let them ſinke in their ſin, til they come to the bottome of hell, which is of old for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; who ſees not the whole world is rocked aſleep in the cradle of ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, wallowing in their ſins like fiſhes in the ſea? ſo that we may take vp that complaint which the Lord proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med from heauen in the daies of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſea,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21561:5"/> ſaying, <hi>The Lord hath a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie with the world,</hi> becauſe there is no truth, mercy, nor know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, but by ſwearing, and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſtealing, and whoring they breake out, and bloud toucheth bloud: and being thus frozen in their dregs, hauing made a league with death, &amp; a couenant with hell it ſelfe, they are of the ſame minde with theſe people of whom we ſpake, ſaying, Yet let no man rebuke or reproue another: for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are as they that rebuke the Prieſt; not onely deſpiſing instruction, and refuſing admonition, but they mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure at <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aron,</hi> and are ready to stone <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> the two Captaines of the Lords hoſt, and we are become their enemies for telling them the truth. Howbeit, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the eies of mercifull men are ſet vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; labouring to ſaue their ſoules from being condemned with the world, beſeeching them to breake vp
<pb facs="tcp:21561:6"/> the fallow ground of their hearts that the Lord might raine righteouſnes vpon them, they are ready to giue them <hi>Steuens</hi> reward for his ſweet Apology,<note place="margin">Acts 7.</note> and though they haue not the authority of the Magistrate, yet with the vnruly euill of the tongue, they aſsemble themſelues (as the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſpeaketh) ſaying; <hi>Come, let vs ſmite them:</hi> but how, with ſwords or ſtaues? no ſurely, but with the curſed weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the tongue, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the cuſtome of al wicked men fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time, with reprochings &amp; reuilings, &amp; with their venemous ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, as much as in them lies, to ſhut and pierce thorow the hearts of the Saints of God, with that odious and damnable name of Hypocrite and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembler, ſo that we may ſay with the Prophet <hi>Ieremy: We are in deriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dayly, euery one mocketh vs:</hi> and as he ſaith elſe where; <hi>Woe is me that my mother hath borne
<pb facs="tcp:21561:6"/> me a contentious man, whomall the world hateth.</hi> Yea ſurely ſo far may we be from ſtirring one another vp in this kinde, that wee may weep and ſigh in ſecret, as diuers of the Saints of God haue done, &amp; wiſh with this Prophet, <hi>Oh that my head were full of water, and mine eies a fountaine of teares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 9.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>that I might weep day and night for the ſlaine of the daughters of my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple! Oh that I had in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe a cottage of waifaring men!</hi> Yea ſurely if the wil of the Lord were, we could wiſh with the Prophet, that we had the wings of a Doue, that wee might flie to the vttermoſt parts of the earth, that we might be out of the reach &amp; rage of the wicked men; but ſuch is the zeale of the glory of God, wherwith his children are inflamed, &amp; ſuch is the nature of faith, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with their hearts are touched, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the large promiſes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb facs="tcp:21561:7"/> they are allured, that in deſpight of diuels or men, they haue alwaies made conſcience of this duty. Hence it is, that in the ſcriptures wee haue ſo many examples of this kinde. It was <hi>Peters</hi> commiſsion that when he was conuerted, hee muſt ſtrengthen his brethren. The woman of Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, when Chriſt came to her conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhe hideth it not vnder a buſhell, but runneth into the city with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen proclamation, ſaying to her neighbours: Come, ſee a man that told mee all that euer I did. Yea wee finde that this hath alwaies beene ſo preciſely obſerued that the children of God haue neuer neglected it in the time of greatest affliction that euer they did vndergoe; onely two ſhall ſuffice in ſtead of many: whereof the firſt is in the Lamentations, where the Church ſpeaketh after this manner: <hi>Haue you no regard all you that paſſe by this way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lament. 1 12.</note> 
               <hi>to behold and
<pb facs="tcp:21561:7"/> ſee where there is any ſorrow like vnto my ſorrow, which is done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, wherewith the Lord hath afflicted mee in the day of his fierce wrath?</hi> Wherein wee ſee the perpetuity of the loue of the children of God towards their Brethren, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen when they were at deaths doore they called vpon their neighbours to make vſe of the iudgements of GOD. Anſwerable to this, is that famous example of the Theefe on the Croſſe, who notwithſtanding the dolour and paine wherein he languiſhed, yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing the deſperate and fearefull e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of his fellow that hee was in, ſharply reproueth him, and vſeth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers arguments and reaſons to moue him to lay hold of the Sauiour of the world as he had done before he died. Theſe examples no doubt together with the reaſons aboue ſpecified, moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued this new conuert (being alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuned by diuers of his acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance)
<pb facs="tcp:21561:8"/> to publiſh this litle Treatiſe, as a fruit of his thankfulneſſe, like <hi>Dauid</hi> that would not offer a ſacrifice of that which coſt him nothing; and yet hath (as it ſeemeth to me) ſome bluſh or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance, with that zeale where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the holy Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed, when hauing receiued ſpecial benefits from the Lord, he hath theſe words:<note place="margin">Pſalm. 66.</note> 
               <hi>Oh come hither all you that feare God, and I will tell you what the Lord hath done for my ſoule:</hi> making open proclamation as it were vpon the Theater of the world, or as he ſpeaketh, when hauing felt that ſweetneſse, of the which this author had a taſt, he laboureth preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to impart it to others, ſaying, <hi>taſte and ſee how gracious the Lord is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 34.</note> 
               <hi>bleſſed is the man that truſteth in him;</hi> euer vſing a borrowed ſpeech fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar to our ſenſes, taken from the faſhion of Merchants, who hauing brought ſome rare and coſtly commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity
<pb facs="tcp:21561:8"/> from beyond the ſeas, are wont to permit a taſte, and giue a ſight, to the end the buyer may be the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to accept of the ſame. And true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this is the practiſe of this new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted Prentiſe, who hauing lien a long time ſleeping in ſecurity, eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming highly of the things of this vaine world, till it pleaſed the Lord in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to looke vpon him the ſcales falling from his eies,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.8.</note> ſo that hee perceiued the Lord comming vnto him, skip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ouer hilles, and leaping ouer mountaines (meaning his ſinnes, as may appeare by that we read in Rom <hi>8.</hi> as one awaked out of a dreame, he maruailed and reioiced greatly at his wonderful deliuerance, and being deſirous to make many partakers of his happineſse, he taketh his penne and writeth this little Treatiſe and Labor of loue, conſiſting in (foure) ſpeciall heads, as appeareth in the firſt leafe of this booke, concerning the manner of
<pb facs="tcp:21561:9"/> it you are not to expect much painted eloquence, filed phraſes, figures, allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which haue little vſe more then to tickle the eares; but euen with all humility and meeknes, out of his own experience, wiſheth comfort by the comfort wherwith he was comforted, of God. Heere I remember part of a story in <hi>Samuel,</hi> where it is thus written:<note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.8</note> 
               <hi>And</hi> Eliab <hi>his eldeſt bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heard when he ſpake vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and was very angry with</hi> Dauid, <hi>and ſaid, why commeſt thou down hither, &amp; with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haſt thou left the ſheep? I know thy pride &amp; the malice of thine heart.,</hi> &amp;c. Euen ſo I feare mee, there be many Eliabs ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior to the yong ſeruant of God <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> that will not onely impute this worke to pride of heart, but wil aske, With whom hast thou left thy ſheep? that is, how hee hath diſcharged his duty to his maſter, iudging it a matter vnlawfull for him to meddle
<pb facs="tcp:21561:9"/> withall, becauſe hee ſhall offer iniury to his maſter in the practiſe hereof. For anſwere whereunto, we are to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue a difference according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and quality of the place and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; Some ſeruice perhaps will warrant that, which others do vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deny them: for art thou an artifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer and of an occupation? thou haſt not this liberty without extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary allowance of thy master. On the contrary, is hee a trades man, and vſing trafficke? then the moſt and chiefest of his buſineſse is in receiuing and deliuering of commodities, in the which much vacant time is idly ſpent: and happy are you, and bleſt of God, that haue ſuch a ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; you may be ſure to be wel &amp; faithfully dealt withal in the charge commited vnto him, when others are wickedly abuſed. But if this ſuffice not, know you that hee had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary allowance of his kind and fauourable maſter. Moreouer, I am
<pb facs="tcp:21561:10"/> of that priuity and acquaintance with him, that I may proteſt in the ſight of God, and before men, that this ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Prentiſe, and ſanctified yong man, hath vſed of his owne ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous diſpoſition, to riſe two or three houres in the morning, before he was imploied in his maſters affaires, which as it was a thing commendable, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from a good inclination: ſo ſurely now is it much more praiſe worthy, being found in the way of righteouſneſse, becauſe the teachers therof are highly to be commended, ſo that we are not alwaies to reproue and contemne ſeruants in this kinde, leſt in ſo doing we giue a hard cenſure of <hi>Dauid</hi> himſelfe, (of whom we ſpake euen now.) But happily you will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and ſay, that <hi>Dauid</hi> came in zeale of Gods glory, to take the ſhame from Iſrael, which was much diſhonored by the vncircumciſed Philiſtine, a fearefull, great and huge monſter. In
<pb facs="tcp:21561:10"/> nature I anſwere that, <hi>Goliah</hi> neuer blaſphemed the Lord of hoſts more then wee, nor euer had more fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and toes of deformity, I meane Papiſts and Atheists, which are in indeed the weapons &amp; naturall liues of our ſpirituall <hi>Goliah,</hi> ſo that the cauſe then of both being not much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, the anſwere that followeth ſhall not vnfitly be applied, though not in the ſame meaſure of grace, wiſedome and modeſty, yet in the ſame nature of zeale, truth and ſincerity: anſwer with him in the <hi>29.</hi> verſe: Graue Fathers, maſters and ſuperiors, what haue I done, is there not cauſe? But if this Apology ſeeme vnſufficient, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue with me breefly the benefit that commeth hereby, and the fault conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered will eaſily be wiped away. In the firſt place then it bringeth a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to the Church of God, when they ſhall ſee the propheſies fulfilled, and thoſe promiſes performed which long
<pb facs="tcp:21561:11"/> ſince was declared to fall out in the latter age of the world,<note place="margin">Eſay. 11.9.</note> that the earth ſhall bee filled with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Lord,<note place="margin">Ioel. 8.</note> as the ſea is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with with waters. Againe, <hi>Your daughters ſhall propheſie, your old me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal dreame dreames &amp; your yong men ſhal ſee viſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 8.</note> 
               <hi>And alſo vpon the ſeruants will I powre out my ſpirit.</hi> Againe, <hi>Out of the mouth of Babes haſt thou or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained ſtrength, becauſe of their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</hi> Notwithſtanding theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies, I grant, chiefly fulfilled at the comming of Christ, yet in reſpect of the perpetuity of it, it is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine vntill the number of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect be accompliſhed; yea, and wee that are now liuing haue ſeene the extraordinary power and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of it, if wee conſider ſince the time of <hi>Luther,</hi> how the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell flying from the middeſt of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,<note place="margin">Reuel. 14.6</note> hauing an euerlasting Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell
<pb facs="tcp:21561:11"/> in his mouth to preach to the nations that dwell vpon the earth, ſaying with a loud voice: <hi>Feare GOD, giue glory to him:</hi> an vnſpeakeable and peculiar fauour of GOD, as our Sauiour Chriſt ſayeth; <hi>Bleſſed are the eies that ſee thoſe things which you ſee, and the eares that heare thoſe things which you heare;</hi> being the onely meanes to bring vs into the fauour of God and men, that it may bee ſayed of vs,<note place="margin">Cant. 6.9.</note> as it was of his owne ſpouſe: <hi>Who is this that loeketh forth as the morning, faire as the Moone, pure as the Sunne, terrible as an armie with banners?</hi> Yea then we ſhall bee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to the Lord, who ſo toucheth vs, toucheth the apple of his eie, and hee will ſay to our enemies:<note place="margin">Cant. 3.5</note> 
               <hi>I charge you O you daughters of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, by the Roe, &amp; by the Hindes of the field, that you ſtirre not vp
<pb facs="tcp:21561:12"/> nor waken my beloued vntill ſhee pleaſe.</hi> Yea then ſhall wee be ſet as a ſeale vpon his heart, and as a ſignet vpon his arme: for loue is ſtronger then death: Ieloſie is cruell as the graue, the coales thereof are fiery coles, and a vehement flame: much water cannot quen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r loue, neither can the flouds drowne it. If a man would giue al the ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his houſe for loue the world would greatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne it.<note place="margin">Cant. 8.1</note> Secondly, it much aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, declareth, and ſetteth forth the power of the Goſpell; when men are made of Lions, Lambs, their natures being changed, that they come wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly in the day of aſſembly, the loue of God conſtraining them and the bleſsing of God vpon them, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing their ſonnes to bee as the plants growing vp in their youthes, &amp; their daughters as the corner stones gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen aft r the manner of <hi>Apelles,</hi> &amp;c. So that other nations being
<pb facs="tcp:21561:12"/> our Iudges are forced to ſay of vs:<note place="margin">Pſal. 144.7</note> 
               <hi>Happy are the people that are in ſuch a caſe, yea bleſſed are the people whoſe God is the Lord</hi> Iehoua. Thirdly, it is exceeding com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable; and no leſse honorable to the graue fathers, and faithfull lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned preachers of our age, when they ſhall ſee the bleſsing of God vpon their labours, &amp; their children which they haue begotten into the faith by the word of truth:<note place="margin">Pſalm. 127</note> like arrowes in the hand of the strong man, and are not aſhamed to ſpeake before their enemies in the gate. So that they haue no neede of the approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men, or letters of recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions their Epistles being written not with inke &amp; paper, but in the hearts of their children, and ſhineth in the world to the praiſe and glory of God.</p>
            <p>Laſtly a notable motiue &amp; prouoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to incite and ſtir vp the minds of
<pb facs="tcp:21561:13"/> thoſe that are too ſlacke and negligent in this kinde, and may alſo be vſed as a whetstone to ſharpen and ſet an edge vpon finer wits, that ſo all the members of Chriſt both learned and vnlearned, may meet and ioine foot to foot, and ſhoulder to ſhoulder, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelues againſt their great &amp; common aduerſary, and being dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by one ſpirit, may vtter their voices both by praier &amp; by preaching, that we may cauſe the kingdome of Antichriſt to fall downe like the walles of Iericho; that ſo, if it be the Lords will, we that are now liuing may ſee that with the eies of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw ſo long ſince with the eies of his ſpirit, and ſo with holy reioycing and gladneſſe of heart, we may ſay with bleſſed Saint <hi>Iohn; It is fallen, it is fallen, great Babylon, and is become a cage of vncleane birds.</hi> Now if any ſhall aske of me, who are you, and what is
<pb facs="tcp:21561:13"/> your name, whoſe iudgement the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhould ſo much reuerence? In this behalfe, I anſwere: If I were one of learning and eſtimation, perhaps I might cary thee away not vſing any great reaſon or demonstration. On the contrary, if of no note and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, thou wouldeſt hardly be brought to embrace it, though I bring ſtrong and forceable arguments and reaſons. I refer thee therefore to the booke it ſelfe, which is able to commend it ſelfe, to the conſcience of any indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent reader, whoſe eares being ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied trieth words, as the mouth taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth meat. Onely this I will ſay with the Aapoſtle <hi>Iames;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 34.3.</note> 
               <hi>Haue not the faith in reſpect of perſons:</hi> and then I dare aſſure my ſelfe the Lord ſhall haue glory, and his chi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ldren com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. The which vpon the knees of my ſoule, I craue of his goodnes, and that he will increaſe in the hearts of his Saints ſauing faith, and with faith
<pb facs="tcp:21561:14"/> vertue, and with vertue, knowledge, and with knowledge temperance, and with temperance patience, and with patience godlineſſe, and with godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse brotherlie kindneſſe, and with brotherlie kindneſse loue, that you may make your calling and election ſure, ſo that you may neuer fall.</p>
            <p>By him that praieth daily for the peace of Sion, and longeth to ſee Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem in her pefect beautie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:21561:14"/>
            <head>The contents of the Chapters <hi>following in this Booke.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> Of Gods graces and benefits, in free mercy beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon man, that thereby hee may be moued to ſerue his diuine ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty. fol. <hi>1. 2. 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Of the infinit and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable benefit of Chriſts death, &amp; m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns great ingratitude notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, which all things whatſoeuer in their kinde condemne. fol. <hi>4.5.6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Of the moſt miſerable estate of the Reprobate both in this world and in the world to come, as alſo of the moſt bleſſed &amp; happy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, heere and hence, of thoſe who feare God. fol. <hi>11. 12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> Of mans fooliſh and
<pb facs="tcp:21561:15"/> fearefull delay of praier and true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, till the vncerten houre of death and ſudden departure. fol. <hi>19. 20.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> Of Gods manifold and good meanes to bring vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and reconciliation with him, if we haue any ſparke of grace in vs, <hi>28.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> Of three excellent meanes of good gouernement. fol. <hi>38. 39.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> Of the good meanes to awake vs out of the ſleep of ſinne, and to quicken vs to a new conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. fol. <hi>47. 48.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 8.</hi> Of mans lamentable frailty and weakneſſe euer to bee ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected, and the deſire hee ſhould haue to be reconciled with God in Chriſt. fol. <hi>53. 54.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 9.</hi> Of true repentance &amp; the notable benefit therof fol. <hi>59. 60.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP. 10.</hi> of the excellent good,
<pb facs="tcp:21561:15"/> and profit of afflictions to Gods true children. fol. <hi>67.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Laſtly, two praiers annexed to bee ſaid in a priuate family both morning and euening.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device. Ornament of a lion's face over a shield and two owls. McKerrow number 215Β.</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:21561:16"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21561:16"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Prentiſes practiſe</hi> in godlines, and his true freedome.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was a notable ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (my deere and welbeloued brethren in Chriſt) whoſoeuer was the Author, That there is nothing great on earth but Man, and nothing great in man but his ſoule; and therefore as all creatures admire and ſerue, and benifit man the wonder of the world; ſo ſhould man himſelfe alſo admire and tender, and ſeeke the behoofe &amp; aduancement of his ſoule the wonder of wonders: for this is our glory, our crowne, our perfection, our very
<pb facs="tcp:21561:17"/> life; ſaue this and ſaue all.</p>
               <p>But I know not how it comes to paſſe: This which ſhould bee our cheefe and onely care, the moſt part of men caſt behind their backes; and they that are taken to husband other matters well and prudently, in this are ſo vnthrifty and ill husbands, that they ſet all at ſix and ſeuen, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer that onely pretious thing (which ouerballanceth the whole world) to go to irrecouerable wracke and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine.</p>
               <p>So that the Lords prophets of our time, haue euen as iuſt cauſe as euer <hi>Ieremie</hi> had, to take vp that ſad com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint:<note place="margin">Ier. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>The earth is fallen to vtter deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, for that there is no man that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth in his heart,</hi> no man that ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth aright his owne eſtate: <hi>Iere.</hi> 12. But Atheiſme and prophanenes, and ſecure licentiouſnes, haue gotten ſuch ſway, that ſcarſe any man beleeues God to be God, ſcarſe any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thinks hee hath a ſoule to ſaue, they laugh, they make merrie, they feaſt, they frolick, they ſing care away all the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21561:17"/> day long, as if heauen were but a dreame, hell but a fable, the ſoule an idle title of a thing which is not, and themſelues ſent hither to no other end but to ſport and play, and follow the luſts and vanities of their wicked hearts. The Lord hath planted vs in a good ſoile, he hath put freſh earth about vs, he hath prunde vs, and ſet a ditch and a wall to incircle &amp; fence vs, and now he longeth for the firſt ripe fruits, and we are all become like the ſummer gatherings, there is not a cluſter to preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto him. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many a time ere this, but that ſome good vinedreſſer hath entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wee may ſtand yet one yeare lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, there had beene ſet to vs a hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet &amp; a fire (an vnquenchable fire) the iuſt reward of ſuch vnprofitable trees, as doe but cumber the ground wherein they grow.</p>
               <p>O my brethren, that we would be once but ſo wiſe as to ſee our folly, &amp; the fearefull danger wee ſtand in by meanes thereof. Hath God created vs in his owne Image, that we ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:21561:18"/> thus vilely &amp; continually deface his glorious likenes? Hath Chriſt redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vs from the power of the Diuel with no leſſe price the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his owne hart bloud, that voluntarily wee ſhould caſt our ſelues into the bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan? Hath he by offering vp him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for vs, purged vs from ſin, that we ſhould afreſh run headlong to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannes? Hath he therefore made vs heires of heauen, that through our owne default we ſhould be firebrands of hell? Hath hee therefore ſaued our ſoules, that we ſhould negligently &amp; wilfully caſt away ſoules and bodies for euer.</p>
               <p>Where is our zeale to God-ward? where is our reuerent feare of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty? wher is our Chriſtianity? where is our faith and godlines? where is our thankes we giue to the Lord for his ſo innumerable benefits? where is our ſeruice &amp; obedience we yeeld to our Lord Ieſus Chriſt for his ſauing health? nay where is our very reaſon wherein wee differ from bruit beaſts, who by nature are lead to deſire and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21561:18"/> follow things profitable to them, &amp; to ſhun the hurtfull: and yet we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the direction of reaſon, &amp; the illumination of grace beſides, haue no deſire of euerlaſting profit, nor feare of endleſſe deſtruction?</p>
               <p>What if God ſhould inſtantly ſend forth the decree of his wrath vpon vs to roote vs out of the Land of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and would receiue no interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or atonement for vs, as he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his owne people when they had prouoked him to wrath, that though <hi>Noe, Iob</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> ſhould beg for them, yet he would not heare them, nor ſhould his affection bee towards ſuch a people?</p>
               <p>Oh my brethren, if this ſhould bee to vs, it had been good for vs we had neuer beene borne, yea the vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable beaſts and ſenſeleſſe creatures, the moſt vgly things of nature were in happier caſe then wee: for they haue no reckoning to make whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their life is gone out of them, or their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance diſſolued, but then beginneth our wofull audit, then our debts and
<pb facs="tcp:21561:19"/> arrerages ſhalbe produced againſt vs, then ſhall wee heare that heauy ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, <hi>Bind him hand and foote, and caſt him into vtter darknes, whence he ſhal not come out till he haue paid the vttermoſt farthing.</hi> But the Lord in mercy hath yet ſpared vs (though it be not long ſince that he made the graue to open his wideſt mouth vpon vs) it is yet called to day, his eie is yet ready to pitie vs, &amp; his eares are open to heare vs; let vs not harden our hearts and prouoke him as wee haue done with our wickednes and impenitencie, but let vs both ſoundly and ſodainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert to him, and he will receiue vs &amp; imbrace vs, and his fierce wrath ſhall be turned from vs. Oh how well it becomes a man (ſaith the wiſe He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew) when he is reproued,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 20 4.</note> to ſhew repentance, for ſo ſhall hee eſcape wilfull ſinne. Conſider what I ſay, &amp; the Lord giue you and me vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in all things.</p>
               <p>And now let vs enter into ſome larger diſcourſe of this matter, that we may the better ſee our vanitie and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21561:19"/> follie in going on in our ſins, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off our repentance and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (as we doe) from day to day, and from time to time, to the high diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of almightie God, and the feareful hazarding of our owne ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And becauſe I ſpeake to ſuch as are (many) of liberall education, &amp; (all) of good capacitie, and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I will tie my ſelfe to ſome order in the handling hereof, not that I would ſeeme to take ſcholarſhip vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, which I do freely confeſſe I haue not, but for that I haue in other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters found the profit of order, both to the writer, and to him that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</p>
               <p>Firſt therefore I beſeech you, as you loue and tender your owne ſoules (which I doe now loue alſo, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſince I began to loue mine owne) conſider with me not ſlightly, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with a deepe &amp; earneſt thought, the tremblable eſtate of a man vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, and the dangerous inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences we runne into, by our impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitencie and obſtinate perſiſting in
<pb facs="tcp:21561:20"/> our wicked waies. And I truſt (by the cooperation of Gods grace) though euery inconuenience ſeueral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie cannot moue vs, yet all of them iointly together ſhall affect our harts and ſtirre vs vp to ſome more care &amp; conſcience of being that which wee would be called.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmightie GOD, in the creation aſſigned to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing in the world ſome particular end, and impreſſed in their nature, an appetite and deſire to that end continually, as to the very point and ſcope of their being: As we ſee birds make their neſts, and breed vp their yong: beaſts skuffle for their fodder &amp; paſtorage:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21561:20"/> Fiſhes flote vp and downe the riuers; Trees beare fruit; Flowers ſend forth ſweet odours, herbes their ſecret ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; Fire aſpires vpward with all his might; Earth hath no reſt till it come into his proper region: Waters poſt vpon the necke one of another, to the boſome of the maine; Aire puſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it ſelfe into euery open voidnes vnder heauen. This is cleare in our owne obſeruation, and experience: and ſhall wee thinke that man (the moſt noble creature) (for whoſe comming all this pompe and ſhew was ſet in order, as for their Lord and King) was made in vaine, and had not his peculiar end appointed him alſo proportionally to the noblenes of his quality and condition? Yes doubtles, that God that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuer erre nor ouerſee in his workes, allotted vnto man the worſhip and ſeruice of his maker in this world, and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying of the ſame his makers glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for euer in the world to come, as his maine obiect and aiming point, whereto he ought to tend and referre
<pb facs="tcp:21561:21"/> himſelfe all his daies.</p>
               <p>Now for man to ſwarue from this end, and to ſerue the Diuell, the world and his ſenſuall luſts; and being made for heauen, to follow the direct line that leads to hel, is to ſhew himſelfe more baſe and degenerate, then the moſt baſe and brutiſh crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in the world, and to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded &amp; cried out vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by them co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally: for they keep to this day with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out digreſſion, their proper ends and aſſignements, enioined them by their maker in the creation: onely man is irregular, man alone powres out him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, into all kinde of riot and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p>Oh my brethren turne againe, and conſider ſadly of this point; Shal the little Bee and the Emmet ſo careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do Gods worke, and fulfill the taske which hee hath ſet them? ſhal the ſenſeleſſe ſtone, being forced to mount vpward againſt his inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſinke and deſcend againe as faſt, till it come to the center which is his home and end? and ſhall man (the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21561:21"/> of God) runne bias from his end, and do euery other thing more then the worke preſcribed vnto him? ſhal they (ſilly reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>leſſe things) keep a direct courſe without any volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſwaruing, and yet haue no tutor or remembrancer? And ſhall we euen wilfully ſtray and vary, hauing our owne hearts filled full of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding &amp; iudgement, &amp; being ſo many waies called vpon, and pulled by the ſleeue, as it were, beſide?<note place="margin">Gen 6.</note> Shall God take ioy of all other creatures, &amp; one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repent that he made man? what a ſhame of ſhames is this to vs? we read in the prone and groueling faces of beaſtes that they were made but for the earth vpon which they pore: And do we not likewiſe in our owne erect and loftie countenances, that our end is heauen, and heauenly things, as our vpright ſhape, and high-raiſed looks tend thitherward continually. But what ſhal I ſay?<note n="*" place="margin">Iames 4.</note> 
                  <hi>to him that knoweth to do well, and doth it not, to him it is ſinne,</hi> yea finne with a witnes.</p>
               <p>Againe, where as man hauing by
<pb facs="tcp:21561:22"/> his wilfull fall and diſobedience loſt thoſe excellent powers and priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, wherewith at the firſt he was endued; and enthralled himſelfe for euer to ſinne, death and hell; as it was forethreatned he ſhould, if hee did taſt of the forbidden tree: it pleaſed the Lord, out of his vnutterable loue to his choiſeſt peece of workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, to ſend his owne euerlaſting Son out of his boſome to pay downe the ineſtimable ranſome of his inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent bloud for him; &amp; in ſtead of the earthly paradiſe which he had loſt, to giue him heauen (the ſeat of his owne Maieſtie, and the habitation of this Angels and pureſt ſpirits) for his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, conditionally, that for his freedome and bounty he ſhould ſerue the ſame his Lord in holines &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe before him all the daies of his life.</p>
               <p>And ſurely if any <hi>Alien</hi> being by endenization made a member of the ſame body with the naturall children and inheritable to the common liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and commodities, doe willingly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21561:22"/> acknowledge himſelfe bound and anſwerable to the publike lawes of that country wherein he is denized; much more ought we that are forrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and ſlaues by birth, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>franchiſed and made free denizens of heauen, and fellow citizens with the Saints of God; much more (I ſay) ought we in lue of this ſo beneficiall legitimation to conforme our ſelues to the obedience of the heauenly lawes, and ready to execute the moſt iuſt charges which our God and king hath impoſed vpon vs. Ignorance of theſe lawes, none of vs can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend; both becauſe they are ſo ſhort, and compendious (for God deliuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them at firſt but in ten words, and our Sauiour hath ſince abridged thoſe ten into two, compriſing notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in that Epitome the very end of all law and equity) and alſo becauſe wee of all places of the land are by Gods miniſters, the paſtors of our ſoules, ſo plainely and carefully taught them from time to time, as afterward ſhall be ſhewed.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21561:23"/>
               <p>Now then for vs (the premiſſes waighed) to cary ourſelues towards this moſt gracious Lord in ſuch a diſloiall faſhion, to ſhake off the yoke of his precepts, and kicke al his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements aſide one after onother, when they lie in the way of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit or our pleaſure, and to go on with a bold face and a high hand, multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying ſinne vpon ſinne, without any mind of turning to better waies, til we be wrapt with age, or pined with ſicknes, or worne out with ſinne, that euen ſin her ſelfe caſtes vs off, as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruiceable: what rebellion or ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude can there be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>parable to this? O my brethren, is this to ſerue God in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, not one, but all the daies of our life, from the firſt to the laſt? Is this the ſtate of life we hope to go to heauen in? haue the vnſanctified any title of the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance of the Saints? or the children of the Diuell, to the bleſſed freedome of the Sonnes of God? Is their part in the ſaluation of Chriſt, that dayly and hourely crucifie him afreſh, &amp; in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21561:23"/> a iolly ſcoffing brauery, deride his paſſion, as if his backe were broad e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to beare all their filth?</p>
               <p>Do we looke that the Lord ſhould performe the grant when wee faile in the condition? is not our breach of couenant with him a fruſtrating of his indentment with vs? Beleeue it my brethren, beleeue it, whileſt wee remaine in our ſins, the Lords grant remaines void; we cannot claime the benefite of one drop of Chriſts bloud, nor of the leaſt part of his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits: the ſhaken ſword of the Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin hangeth ouer vs, we ſtand bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from the paradiſe of Gods fauor, and liable to the ſeuereſt penalty of thoſe his lawes which we haue viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; onely ſo long as that penalty is not inflicted, ſo long doth the Lord expect if at any time wee will renue our couenant by repentance, and ſo eſcape out of the ſnare of the Diuell, of whom we are holden captiue to do his pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, when we were ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the holy Lauer of Baptiſme
<pb facs="tcp:21561:24"/> (which is as it were the wombe of the Church) where our regeneration or new birth was firſt ſet a foot, we vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a vow to God, which ought of all Chriſtians to be moſt holily obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; that wee would perfect that newe birth of ours euery day more and more by beleeuing his word, obeying his commandements, morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying our fleſh, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>preſſing our luſts, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the diuel, renou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing the world &amp; fighting ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fully vnder his ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all oppoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that finaly hauing finiſhed our courſe we might receiue the crowne of life, which he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to them that continue faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto the death.</p>
               <p>Now our impenitencie &amp; weltring in ſinne, is not onely a not foſtring, but a very killing of our ſpirituall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the firſt ſeede or kernell; a breaking of our vowe to God; nay a very denying of God and his word, an abiect yeelding vs to his and our enemies, a cowardly running away from the ſpirituall battell at the firſt ſtroke ſtriking; a wilfull loſing of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21561:24"/> our immortall garland, and an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to make Chriſt (the great cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and finiſher of our faith) vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to caſheere vs out of his band, as hauing in vs no ſparkle of that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity and braue-mindednes, which ought to be in ſuch as weare his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and beare armes vnder his ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard.</p>
               <p>The wiſedome of the world is, to retaine to the ſtrongeſt part: and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinkes we hauing beene bred vp vnder the worlds wing, ſhould by this time haue taken out that point of wiſedome, and retaine to Gods ſide: for his is the ſtrongeſt and ſureſt ſide. O my brethren, looke backe to your Baptiſme, and learne to amend. Let not the royall <hi>Character</hi> which God hath ſet vpon vs by the miniſtery of his Church be any longer thus vilely blurd and defaced by our enormous ſinnes. Let vs not breake our vow to God, leſt he binde faſt his curſe to vs: Leaue not the Lord of hoſts, to whom we haue giuen our names, and thoſe powerfull legions of his
<pb facs="tcp:21561:25"/> bleſſed Angels (our conſederates and guarders in his quarrel) to ioine with the Diuell, whom we haue defied, &amp; with the world, &amp; ſin and the fleſh, (a ſort of cowardly rebels) which will themſelues cut our throates when we leaſt ſuſpect them. But let vs new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deep our ſelues in the water of contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that will fetch againe the primitiue colour, which was put vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs in the day of our Baptiſme.</p>
               <p>Ouer and beſide all this, whereas the patience and bountifulneſſe, and long ſuffering of our God, in ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vs ſo many yeares, and waiting for our amendment (though in the meane time wee force him to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine that he is <hi>preſſed vnder our ſinnes as a cart is preſſed vnder a hard load of ſheues</hi>) I ſay, whereas this gracious patience of his ſhould leade vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; we by continuing in ſinne, do abuſe his patience, and heape vp greater wrath vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our heads, againſt the day of wrath, and declaration of the iuſt iudgement of God, which will ſuddainely ouertake vs. God is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21561:25"/> prouoked (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) euery day: heere is forbearance: but what followeth? 2. if a man wil not turne (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all Gods waiting) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he wil whet his ſword, &amp; be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his bow, &amp; make rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy his arrows againſt ſuch prouokers.</p>
               <p>When we ſee wrath in a mans face, it is an argument that he will ſtrike, &amp; we are wont to ſhun &amp; giue backe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. Let vs take heed, Gods face lookes very angerly, we haue dared him ſo long, and put him ſo to it, that he cannot hold his fingers, he muſt needes breake out into blowes: And the blowes of his anger are no light ſtripes, but euen deaths wounds, as all the Land from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſheba,</hi> will beare witnes.</p>
               <p>O then my Brethren, if this Lion roare, who wil not tremble &amp; crouch before him? if he knit his browes that meaſureth heauen with his ſpan and waigheth the mountaines in a ballance, &amp; cleaueth the rockes with his voice, who dares looke him in the face, who ſhal be able to abide his frownes? were we as huge and ſtrong
<pb facs="tcp:21561:26"/> as <hi>Behemoth</hi> or <hi>Leuiathan,</hi> hee will ſpurne vs as a chip, and trample vs vnder his feete as the mire in the ſtreetes, if we incenſe his maieſty, or ſtirre vp his wrath and iealouſie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs.<note place="margin">Apoc.</note> The Kings, and great men, and ſtout Captaines and Warriours, hide themſelues in caues, and in holes of the earth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the feare of the Lord when he riſeth vp to be auenged of ſinners.</p>
               <p>O what ſhall the ſhrub in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes do, when the Okes of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> and the <hi>Cedars</hi> of <hi>Libanus</hi> are thus ſhaken! how dare ſuch ſilly wormes and graſhoppers as we, confront the almighty, and prouoke him yearly &amp; hourely with new and new ſinnes, (neuer once renuing our repentance) at the blaſting of the breath of whoſe diſpleaſure the hilles melt, and the foundations of the world ſhake and are remoued? Though he haue worne one rod of peſtilence to the ſtumps vpon vs, and throwne it by, ſtanding and looking at our behauiour after it, he can call for another and another if
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21561:26"/> our great hearts be not come downe, &amp; repentance &amp; a change appearing in our liues; or he hath famine ſwords wild beaſtes, bedlem waters, treaſures of ſnow and haile, lightnings, thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolts &amp;c. or he hath feuers, palſies, gouts, choliks, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kers wolfes, tympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, &amp;c. to ſcourge preſumptuous ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that wil not be warned: his ſtore houſe is neuer vnfurniſhed with rods, and ſcorpions too, if we put him to it. Surely my Brethren we are tranſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formed with <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> into beaſts, and the hearts and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of men taken from vs, if this conſideration moue vs not to abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate our ſins, and ceaſe from our prouocations, wherewith we haue prouoked this God of anger againſt vs, eſpecially when he hath put vp ſo many abuſes and villanies of ours all our life hitherto, wee iuſtly deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing euery moment to be rooted out, and hee being able many thouſand waies to haue executed the ſentence of our deſtruction vpon vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:21561:27"/>
               <head>CHAP. 3.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat which hath beene ſaid in the former chapter, might ſuffice to worke in vs a mind of repentance, and a change of life, if we caried in euery of our breaſts a meeke and docible heart; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the greater number (which farre exceedes the better) haue their eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall part of a harder kind of temper, we muſt beat vpon them with more ſtrokes, &amp; proſecute this matter with further declaration.</p>
               <p>As the weldoing of a man after he is reconciled to God, fils him full of inward peace and comfort and makes him cheereful and confident in all the cumbers and euils of life; ſo it is the property of ſinne to diſcomfort and torment the ſinner, to wound his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to fill his ſoule full of terrour
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21561:27"/> and perplexity, and to aggrauate eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little outward aduerſity.<note place="margin">Iſay.</note> There is no peace ſaith my God, to the wicked; but terrour and trembling is in all their life. They are poſſeſſed with a ſpirit of vnreſt, and held in in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage vnder euery oppreſſion of their owne conceites.<note place="margin">For as they that feare God, need feare no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo they that feare not him ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not chooſe but feare all things.</note> * <hi>The vngodlie flie</hi> (ſaith Salomon) <hi>whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> none purſueth him, but the righteous is confident as a Lion.</hi> And <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Leuit.</hi> amongſt other euils threatned to the tranſgreſſors of Gods commandements alleageth this: <hi>The wagging of a leafe ſhall make them afraid, they ſhall flee as if a ſword did chaſe them, and they ſhall fall no man purſuing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> And elſe where directing his ſpeech to the ſame men: <hi>The Lord</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>ſhall giue thee a trembling heart, and dazeling eies, and ſorowe of mind; Thy life ſhall hang before thee, and thou ſhalt feare both night and day, and ſhalt haue none aſſurance of thy life: In the morning thou ſhalt ſay, would God it were euening, &amp; at euening thou ſhalt ſay, wold God it were morning: for the feare of thine heart which thou ſhalt feare, and for the
<pb facs="tcp:21561:28"/> ſight of thine eies, vvhich thou ſhalt ſee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A miſerable ſtate of all thoſe men of reprobate mindes, which haue ſold themſelues to worke wickednes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, and caſt the feare of the Lord behinde them; they dread euen the ſafeſt things, and the more they offend the more they feare, their whole life is a butchery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, and all their daies as the daies of a priſoner that is condemned. They thinke euery little cracke to be the voice of ruine, and euery idle ſound, the forerunner of deſtruction. The beames of their chambers ſeeme to deceiue them, and the walles and raf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to lay hold vpon them, their own ſhadow is ſuſpected to betray them and the ſtones of the ſtreet to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire againſt them; whereſoeuer they go they thinke they are deſcried, and Gods executions are out to take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as a man that is far in debt, thinkes in euery window ſtands a creditor to obſerue him, and almoſt euery one he meets to be a Sergeant to arreſt him.</p>
               <p>There lodgeth in the middeſt of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21561:28"/> them a domeſticall fury, which eft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoones breaketh off their beginning reſt, and ſcourgeth them (as one ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) with ſilent laſhes, which are not heard of the neereſt about them. If they be not yet puniſhed, they looke that they ſhall be. If they bee, the preſent feeling of euill induceth ſtill feare of worſe, when one peril is paſt, they thinke another is behinde; and when that is eſcaped yet a greater is to come: ſo ſtill the firſt feare is inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited by the ſecond, and the ſecond by the third, and one by another, that they cannot recouer any ſparkle of confidence, nor promiſe themſelues one minute of ſecurity.</p>
               <p>What they deſerue, that they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect euer, and to expect paine, is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times more painful then to indure paine; euery thing is againſt them, for they are againſt themſelues; whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is ſpoken or read, they feare it is ſpoken and read of them: when any thing is faulted, their owne fault preſently comes in their way. Euerie nod and winck they imagine, notes
<pb facs="tcp:21561:29"/> ſomething concerning them, they are their own accuſer, their owne witnes, their owne iudge, their owne hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, they find no place to fly vnto, for their conſcience ſtill purſueth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; themſelues of themſelues are wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and thruſt thorow. Aske of the daies of old, and they will ſpeake it, &amp; the yeares of paſſed generations, and they will confirme it, that thoſe ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors &amp; diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forts are the fruits of ſin: inquire of <hi>Caine, Baltazar, Saul, Iudas, Nero, Iulian,</hi> and they will all cry with one voice, that the pangues, prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, vnreſts, and frights appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate to all wicked impenitent perſons, are (as it were) certaine flaſhes of the flames of hell fire. But what need we raiſe vp ſuch a cloud of ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed witneſſes to confirme the point we haue in hand? ſpeake any wicked man amongſt vs (and let his tongue be a true embaſſador) whether hee feele not in himſelfe ſome meaſure of this forlornnes, whether his hart bee not often as cold as a ſtone in his bellie, &amp; all his ſtrength <hi>as water powred out vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:21561:29"/> the earth.</hi> And though he ſtrengthen himſelfe and ſtriue neuer ſo to expell from his minde this vncheerefulnes and daſtardly faintnes, borrowing many times of the bodie the ſolace &amp; delight of ſome counterfeit pleaſures, whereby he may ſeeme to haue ſome peace (like the ſick man, who in his ſleepe feeleth not his paine) yet after that ſhort and ſower mingled ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes he returnes to the chaine of his old bondage, &amp; his wonted gripings ſeaze afreſh vpon him.</p>
               <p>O my brethren, this biting memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ſinne, this worme of conſcience which will not bee bribed, this pale hartleſnes that ſeazeth vpon vs when the offence is committed, makes the moſt obdurate ſinner ſomtimes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and condemne his owne doings; and to ſay to himſelfe, <hi>Sure, to do well is farre better.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This makes the moſt impudent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterer to think ſometimes the chaſt married bed to yeeld more contented reſt, then the wanton couch of the ſtrange woman.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21561:30"/>
               <p>This makes the dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kard ſometimes to thinke the moderate vſe of Gods creatures with thankeſgiuing, to bee much better both for body and ſoule, then his vaine and beaſtly exceſſes.</p>
               <p>This makes the murtherer and furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous man ſometimes to preferre peace and gentlenes before the bloudy ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or the quarrelling tongue.</p>
               <p>This makes the ſpitefull wretch, to thinke him that loueth and benefiteth another, to be more bleſſed and belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of God, then hee that with a low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring brow plotteth and practiſeth for his neighbours hurt.</p>
               <p>This makes the deceitfull tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to thinke ſometimes one wel got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten groat in trueth and conſcience, to be greater riches then many pounds of wicked thrift.</p>
               <p>This makes the couetous oppreſſor to thinke ſometimes the liberall Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner and good houſekeeper to bee more acceptable to God &amp; makes then the greedy churle that makes the poore offer to his box, and wrings pence out of the hirelings wages.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:21561:30"/>
               <p>O why ſhould wee delight in euill when the Authors themſelues are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed at it, and aſſure vs that vpon the reckoning there is nothing but terrour and diſcomfort to bee gained by it?</p>
               <p>And why ſhould we not loue wel doing, when the very enemies ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of commend it? as being the ground of a quiet conſcience, and that is like a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall feaſt, where there is mirth and cheare all the day long. O my brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is the inward purenes of the heart that neuer makes vs change co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour: it is innocencie that neuer galles the mind, neuer pricks the inward parts: it is ſeaſonable repentance that breedes that internall glee, which is a certaine taſte of the future felicity, and a beginning of the ioyes of heauen in vs, and that which maketh vs feele incredible pleaſures amidſt the moſt greuous troubles &amp; miſeries of this life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Once</hi> (ſaith a godly writer) <hi>man was in paradiſe: Now paradiſe is in man, and that is the ioy of a good conſcience:</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21561:31"/> which makes him confident and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and reſolute at all times; ſo that though the heauen ſhould melt, and the earth be remoued, yet he is vnſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, for he knoweth in whom he hath beleeued, and if the Lord be God, he ſhall not miſcary.</p>
               <p>Wouldeſt thou haue this ſecurity, this peace, this boldnes? wouldeſt thou liue this bleſſed life? wouldeſt thou bee without frights, without checks, without prickings in thy hart? then fly from ſinne, abandon all that may offend the Maieſty of GOD, worke out your ſaluation with feare and trembling, ſeek the Lord, cal vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, truſt in him, thanke him, ſweare not by his ſacred name; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane not his ſabbaths, kil not, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell not, hate not in thy heart, let not the ſunne go downe vpon thy wrath; defile not thy body through luſt; co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen not, oppreſſe not, ſlander not, couet not another mans, labour to ſay truely both now and to your liues end, that thou maiſt ſay with the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtle,<note place="margin">Acts. 24.</note> I haue <hi>endeauoured to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21561:31"/> walke in all good conſcience alwaies, both towards God and towards men;</hi> and that ſame peace of God which paſſeth all vnderſtanding, ſhall keepe your hearts and mindes in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</p>
               <p>But if you let go the raines to your old licentiouſnes, and bee more wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to day, then yeſterday, &amp; to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, then to day; if you ſay to the good motions of Gods ſpirit, as the falſe friend in <hi>Salomon</hi> to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, <hi>Go, and come againe to morrow:</hi> or as Feſtus to Paul, <hi>when I haue a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient time, I will heare further of you:</hi> and ſo paſſe along your daies in all iollity &amp; voidnes of care (your things ſeeming to be in peace becauſe the ſtrong man hath full poſſeſſion of all) yet when the leaſe of your life ſhal be expired, and the parting houre is come vpon you, then your ſin which ſlept before the dore, ſhall ſtart vp &amp; lie heauy vpon your ſoule and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; and then howſoeuer the Lord may haue ſuffered you to thriue, and grow great in the world, yet you ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:21561:32"/> find that it is not your ſoft beds, nor your pretious waters, nor your ſweet muſick, nor your pleaſant company, nor your ſealed bags, nor your rich purchaſes nor your ſtatutes and eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences can eaſe your minde, or buy you this peace, this bleſſing, this ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable treaſure, which a religious life might haue purchaſed before.</p>
               <p>Beyond all this, whileſt we remain impenitent, GOD heareth not our prayers.<note place="margin">Pſal. 66.</note> 
                  <hi>If I incline my heart to any vvickedneſſe, the Lord vvill not heare me:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>the ſacrifice of the wicked is abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to the Lord, nay their very prayer is turned into ſinne.</hi> And what comfort can wee looke for in the troubles and dangers incide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to our life, when that which ſhould bee our refuge &amp; ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to reſort to, encreaſeth our dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and in ſtead of bearing of the ſtorme, falles downe like a ruinous houſe vpon our heads? we are beſides out of the compaſſe of Chriſts inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, he excepts worldings &amp; wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ones by name out or his prayers: And if he will not plead our cauſe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21561:32"/> who dares ſpeake for vs? if wee bee out of his protection, where is our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance? any deſperate villanie, may ſtrick his dagger to our heart: the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell may teare vs in peeces, and carry vs to hell, there is none to ſuccour vs.</p>
               <p>Moreouer whileſt we take part with ſinne againſt God, all the creatures take Gods part againſt vs: the horſe hath his heeles ready to ſtrike out our breath, the bull hath his hornes rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to goare vs, the boare his tuskes to haunch vs, the dog his phangs to pull out our throates, the tiles ouer our heads are preſt to braine vs, the fly in our cup to choake vs, our owne knife is ready to glance into our fleſh, euery thing elſe is ready to worke miſchiefe to vs, euery little iob vnder our feete to giue vs a bruſing fall, and they doe onely wait while the word be giuen them, and they wil inſtantly accompliſh their charge.</p>
               <p>Beſides, ſo long as we continue to worke euill in the ſight of the Lord and doe not turne vnto him with all
<pb facs="tcp:21561:33"/> our harts, and thinke vpon his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements to doe them, nothing ſhall be ſuccesfull vnto vs;<note place="margin">Mal. 2.2.</note> God will curſe our bleſſings, &amp; our waies ſhall not proſper, wee ſhall bee curſed in the citie, and curſed in the field; cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhall our basket be &amp; our dough; curſed ſhall be the fruit of our bodie,<note place="margin">Deut. 28</note> and the fruit of our land; and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of our cattell; curſed ſhall wee be when wee go our, and curſed alſo when wee come in.</p>
               <p>The Lord ſhall ſend vpon vs cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and trouble, and ſhame, in all that wee ſet our hand to doe.</p>
               <p>Marke yet further how particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Lord goeth on with his threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings. Thou ſhalt betroth a wife, and another man ſhall lie with her, thou ſhalt build a houſe, &amp; ſhalt not dwell therein, thou ſhalt plant a vineyard, and ſhall not eate the fruit thereof.</p>
               <p>The ſtranger that is among you ſhall clime vp aboue on high, &amp; thou ſhalt come beneath alowe, he ſhall be thy head, and thou ſhalt bee the taile. Thou ſhalt bee contemned in thine
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21561:33"/> owne country.</p>
               <p>Thou ſhalt neuer but ſuffer wrong &amp; violence alwaies, ſo that thou ſhalt be euen mad for the ſight which thine eies ſhall ſee: things ſhall go ſo croſſe notwithſtanding all thy prouidence and induſtrie, that it ſhall make thee at thy wits end to thinke of it.</p>
               <p>O my Brethren who would conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in ſinne one houre longer, that ſeeth himſelfe hemd in on euerie ſide with ſo many curſes and iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, as it were ſo many armies of the Lord fighting directly againſt him? who would lay his eies together, before he had made his peace with God, and once for euer bid defiance to his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſins? who would liue this wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched life ful of vexation and terrour, and curſing; forlorne of God and his creatures, &amp; deſtitute of all ſuccours, without any care to redreſſe it, till he be come to ſhake hands with it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may preſently redreſſe it by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent reconciliation with God; when by caſting off ſinne in this houre, he may in this houre caſt off al theſe cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb facs="tcp:21561:34"/> and miſeries accompanying ſinne, and ſo both liue a bleſſed life all his time, and cloſe vp his daies with a bleſſed death, which ſhall be the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of eternall life? what fooliſh bodie wouldly forty or fifty yeares mortally languiſhing of ſome diſeaſe, refuſing to be cured all his beſt time and ſeeking helpe onely in his laſt worſt time, when the cure is doubt full, by reaſon nature is decayed, or if he recouer, yet he cannot enioy his health aboue a day or a weeke, or a month, and then giue ouer life &amp; all? But ten thouſand times worſe infatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated are they that would lie the whole age of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a mortall languiſhment of ſoule (as it were bedred by reaſon of ſinne) and neuer take the phyſick of repentance, till they lie gaſping for breath, when it is vncertaine whether they ſhall then haue leaſure to repent, or if they repent, whether it will be of force and able to fetch life in the ſoule being ſo farre gone in that deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate conſumption: or if they reco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer and liue the true life, (which rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21561:34"/> happens) they liue in a ſort too late both to themſelues and others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 4.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hey haue euer proued vnprofitable in religion that haue held too much of that truantly rule <hi>the way to well doing is neuer too late.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ.</note> Therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> calles vpon yong men to remember their Creator in their yong daies, as if well doing were <hi>neuer too ſoone.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 3.13.</note> And the A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſtle exhorteth the Hebrues to call one vpon another, to turne to God. whileſt it is called to day; not to make it a morrowes worke: his reaſon is Leſt any of you be hardned through the deceitfulnes of ſinne. See heere then one maine danger of dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in our ſinnes, and putting off
<pb facs="tcp:21561:35"/> our amendment from one day to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: the longer we continue in ſinne, the more we are hardened in ſinne, ſo that at length wee cannot repent, no though wee ſeeke it with teares, as <hi>Eſau</hi> did. It is as eaſie to temper the flint ſtone betweene our fingers, and to make it ſoft and pliable for ſealing; as to ſupple our ſtonie hearts, and fit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to receiue the impreſſion of grace: you thinke you can repent when you will, and apprehend the mercies of God when your owne leaſure ſerues you; but you are deceiued, it is not in man to order his waies, nor to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into the right path, being miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead. Sinne is cunning and will make you beleeue you may come and goe without entanglement or reſtraint; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially whileſt you haue day light enough before you. But truſt not this fleering <hi>Iahel,</hi> for if you vſe to turne in to ſleepe in her tent, and taſt of her milke and butter which ſhe can ſet in a Lordly diſh, ſhe wil (when you ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect leaſt) nayle your head to the ground, that it ſhall be impoſſible to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21561:35"/> get looſe from her.<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.</note> This <hi>Dalila</hi> hath a crue of Philiſtines ready in a corner, when ſhe hath ſhorne the lockes of your ſtrength vpon her lap, to come vpon you and bind you with fetters, and put out your eies, that you ſhall neither haue power to ſtart, nor yet ſee the meanes to make an eſcape.</p>
               <p>In your youth ſhe will teach you to excuſe your miſtreadings, with, <hi>It is the time:</hi> and when that excuſe is out of faſhion by reaſon of more yeares puld ouer your heads, then ſhe will reach you another Apologie, <hi>It hath beene my cuſtome, and I cannot leane it:</hi> and then followeth hardnes of heart that you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not repent (the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that God bringeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a man or woman in this world) for then we are paſt hope, God hath decreed our deſtruction, and all the prayers and ſuffrages of the faithfull (which are of great force) will doe vs no good. God wil anſwere as hee did to <hi>Ieremie: Doe not intreat noe for them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 7.16. &amp; 14.11.</note> 
                  <hi>make no interceſſion to doe them good,</hi> for I wil in no wiſe heare you, I haue
<pb facs="tcp:21561:36"/> thruſt them out of my ſight, &amp; I haue decreed to deſtroy them. Yet you may preuent this iudgement: yet your cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of euil is not ſo ſtrong but you may breake it: yet you may caſt off a litle and a little by good cuſtome, that which you haue got at times by euill cuſtome: yet your hearts are tender &amp; flexible, deferre not the new moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them, til they be growne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe and incorrigible; lay hold of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered grace, whileſt the accepted time &amp; the day of ſaluation laſts Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, he that promiſeth mercie to the penitent, hath not promiſed repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to the preſumer vpon mercy, nor one day of life to the delayer of repentance.</p>
               <p>But you are yong and healthy: what then? therefore you are not like to die? do not lambes skinnes come to be ſold as well as ſheepes skinnes? Doe we not ſee and heare, where euer we go, that men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men die, that were neither ſicke nor old? wee may ſay we will go to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row to ſuch a place, to ſee ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21561:36"/> to receiue ſuch a ſumme of money, to make merry &amp;c. and yet before this next euening may heare that voice; Foole, to preuent thy bargainings, thy talkings, thy merri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp;c. this night before the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, thy ſoule ſhall be taken from thee. Aske but that one ſtreet which leadeth from the City to the common iudgement hall, how many times her ſtones haue beene beſtained with the reeking gore of murdered men, ſince the beginning of this laſt terme; and tell me whether life be ſo ſure a thing when ſo many ſound bodies haue groand their laſt in a peaceable well gouerned City, within the compaſſe of one terme, and the limits of one ſtreet: and how knoweſt thou whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy time be not as ſhort as theirs ſeeing (as I ſaid afore) not onely wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men vpon earth but all the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels in hell, &amp; all the creatures in the world are armed againſt thee, whileſt thou remaineſt impenitent and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſt in thy ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Thou knoweſt how ſhort warning<note place="margin">Eſay. 38.1.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21561:37"/> 
                  <hi>Ezekias</hi> had: <hi>Put thy houſe in order, for thou ſhalt die and not liue.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Numb. 20.25.</note> And <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron: Bring Aron and Eleazar his ſonne vp into mount Hor, and cauſe him to put off his garments, and put them vpon his ſonne,</hi> and then he ſhall die imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately vpon the top of the mount. What if the like warning were giuen thee? where is thy repentance then become? where are thy good purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for hereafter? Then thou wilt cry out; if I had knowne my time had beene ſo ſhort,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ifs</hi> at deaths ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>roch vaine &amp; fooliſh.</note> I would long ere this haue reformed my waies: If it were now to begin my life, I would take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother courſe. In what ſanctimony and vprightnes would I walke before God &amp; man? O that the Lord would ſpare me a little before I goe away from hence, and be no more ſeene! O that he would allowe me but one moneth or one weekes reſpite to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile my ſinnes and ſue for mercy! Wouldſt thou then be a new man? be ſo now; Wouldſt thou then ſeeke Gods fauour? ſeeke it now. Wouldſt thou then amend all faults? amend
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21561:37"/> them now. Why doeſt thou not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent thoſe ifs and conditions, which will then bee but fooliſh thoughts? why doeſt thou not that this day, nay day by day all thy life long, which thou wouldeſt doe at ſuch an extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity ſeeing thou knoweſt not which will be thy laſt day? why doeſt thou not doubt al thy daies &amp; endeuour to be ſuch a one al thy life, as thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt be at the point of death?</p>
               <p>But put caſe thou kneweſt thy life would be lengthned out to ſome for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or fifty yeares more, and that thou wert aſſured not to dy the vtmoſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piration of thoſe yeares: be like then thou wouldſt nothing but follow thy luſtes the while, and thinke the laſt yeare ſoone enough to reforme thee. But blind fooles they are, that are thus conceited: if thou canſt not with the ſtraining of all thy ſinewes pull vp a yong tree of two or three yeares planting, how wilt thou hope to pull it vp, when the ſpurs of the rootes are faſtened deep on euery ſide, and the boughes are like to the couering
<pb facs="tcp:21561:38"/> of a tent ouer thy head? Aſſay to root out but one vice now, whileſt it is freſh and greene and thou ſhalt finde it a matter of ſome paines and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty: and will it be eaſier, thinkeſt thou, ſeuen yeares hence, when the cuſtome of it is growne to a habit or as it were another nature, and the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration therof multiplied to an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred &amp; to a thouſand?</p>
               <p>Say a man were now to carry a bas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket of ſtones fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> London Bridge to I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlington, &amp; ſetting forward about the ſtoopes with the basket on his ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, feeling the waight thereof to pinch and wring him, ſhould preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (like a true louer of his eaſe) ſet it downe againe till another time, and euery day the while, come and put in more ſtones, till it were heape full and running ouer; would you thinke the basket would be lighter at laſt for theſe daily additions, or this man likelier to cary it through then, being grown ruſtie with many yeares ſloth, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it made him ſhrug to ſtand vnder it in the beginning, while his
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21561:38"/> ſtrength was freſh? No, no my deere brethren) the longer we continue in ſinne the fuller and heauier growes the basket, and the vnweldier wee grow that muſt be the porters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Come, come, vp with it, carry it you muſt,</hi> and it will neuer be lighter, nor you better able to beare it, then you be at this preſent; ſtraine your ſelues for a furlong or two, though it ſit vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie at firſt, you ſhall finde it lighter after a little vſe. Better ſmart once, then ake euer; ſet about it &amp; deſpaire not of the ſucceſſe, by conſideration of the difficulty: pray God both humbly and continually to impart vnto you his holy ſpirit, and to ſhed it out in your hearts, through Ieſus Chriſt, that you may compreſſe your owne affections, and by his ſtrength ouercome all impediments, &amp; walke more in all holy obedience before him only be not your owne foe, feed not that ſame humour of lingring, let not looſe the raines to your corrupt affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which cry ſtil, a little more ſleep, a little more ſlumber: For the
<pb facs="tcp:21561:39"/> holy Ghoſt doth not aſſiſt cowards and ſluggards, &amp; ſuch as fit idly with their armes folded together; but thoſe that labour and endeuour earneſtly to tame their naturall wickednes, and to croſſe the ſwing of their luſts, thoſe he deemeth worthy his aide, and they in him, ſhall be more then conquerors. Set your hand to Gods hand, &amp; the worke will be nothing. The violent and reſolute, that breake thorow all oppoſition, they and no other take heauen by maine force.</p>
               <p>But ſay that the Black-moore could change his skin, and the Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard his ſpots, and that you hauing learned all daies of your life to do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, could at the laſt repent and doe wel; yet what an vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfull &amp; vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming thing were it to ſpend your youthful daies in the pleaſures of the world, &amp; the ſeruice of the Diuell, &amp; then to bring your crooked &amp; worne daies to offer to the Lord? To call the Diuell and the world to the feaſt and full diſhes, and let God ſtand at dore waiting (among the beggers)
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21561:39"/> for the reuerſion &amp; ſcraps? The Lord himſelfe is driuen to complaine of this baſe meaſure by his Prophet: <hi>When ye bring the blind for ſacrifices, you ſay it is not euill, and when ye bring the lame and ſick, ye ſay it is good enough for God.</hi> Offer it now to thy Prince; will he be content with thee, or accept thy perſon, ſaith the Lord of hoſtes? <hi>Repent</hi> and be aſhamed of this ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, play not the harlots with God: let none haue the maidenhead of your youth, but your deere Lord &amp; husband: Let none enioy the flower and beauty of your time, but hee that bought you with his precious bloud; you are his, giue him his owne, let him haue it new and faire, not when it is mangled &amp; miſuſed that one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but bluſh in the preſenting of it. Caſt your ſelues into his embrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in your youth &amp; health whileſt you haue ſomething to commend you, &amp; his armes are open to receiue you; ſtay not looking for a better match, this is the beſt that euer you ſhall light on; take it whileſt it is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred,
<pb facs="tcp:21561:40"/> you ſhall neuer repent you of your earlie beſtowing. Hereafter perhaps God will hold you vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of his loue, as hertofore you held him vnworthy of yours; and ſcorne you in your old age and ſicknes, as you ſet not by him in your health and youth. The fiue virgins for lingring but one houre and that in their youth and prime, were ſhut out of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage chamber, and had this anſwere to their knocking, I know you not, you are no friends nor gueſts of mine. And ſhall we thinke the Lord will open vnto vs, and giue vs a cheerful welcome, lingring not houres but yeares, and proſtituting our virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and prime to the world &amp; the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, Gods ſworne enemies? Yet the the doore is open, you may fill your lamps with oile, and be wiſe by their harmes. But if you put it to hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the gates will be ſhut, and all your knocking will be but ſo many fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſtrokes, rebounding vpon your owne hearts.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, whileſt we lie ſoaking in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21561:40"/> ſin and returne euery day to our old vomit; we do pile vp more and more wood for our owne burning. I meane, we do increaſe our accounts againſt that firy day of wrath, which will come vpon as a theefe in the night, in which the heauens ſhall paſſe away with a noiſe, and the element ſhall melt with heat, and the earth with the workes that are therein ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed; then ſhall all the thoughts of our hearts be diſcouered, and an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count required of euery idle word that we haue ſpoken; So ſtrict ſhall that iudgment be. Where wil the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly and ſinner appeare, when the righteous ſhall ſcarſe be ſaued? whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will they turne them when they ſhall ſee the Lambe turned into a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, their Sauiour their Iudge, and their Iudge their witneſſe, againſt whoſe teſtimony, there is no excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; they will wiſh mountaines lay on them to keep them from that mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting: what will theſe differers of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance being preuented and caſt behind by their owne negligence, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb facs="tcp:21561:41"/> for themſelues in that great ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, before the awfull Maieſtie that ſits vpon the throne? with what confuſion and ſhame ſhal they ſtand, when he ſhal ſay vnto them, <hi>I ſent you into the world to doe my will, and you haue done your owne wils?</hi> I allowed you time and meanes to repent, you deſpiſed both time &amp; meanes and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pented not: I gaue you many good motions in your hearts to make you returne vnto me: and you put me off ſtill after ſo long waiting, with, What we will amend; <hi>Did you thinke I would pardon you at laſt? How could you then in common gratitude diſpleaſe ſo gratious a Lord?</hi> Did you thinke I would not pardon you? what madnes beſotted you that you durſt offend me with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope of pardon? I will now ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refie my words which I ſpake by my meſſengers, which I ſent vnto you; Becauſe you haue hardened your hearts againſt me, you ſhal not enter into my reſt: <hi>Goe ye curſed into euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting fire</hi> prepared for the Diuell and his Angels.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21561:41"/>
               <p>O how ſhall theſe impenitent lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerers then take on, howling and rauing, and curſing the day of their natiuity, that the aire ſhal be euen cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with their hideous and gaſtly clamours! And what a comfort will it be to the godly, both yong men and yong maides that haue haue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued God betimes, and takem paines to mortifie their luſts, to ſee the Lord at length proceed in iuſtice againſt the careleſſe wicked ones, which haue liued in all pleaſures and eaſe in this life, when they themſelues haue beene afflicted and maligned and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided, for the profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Goſpel of Ieſus Chriſt?</p>
               <p>O my Brethren and Siſters, when the Lord in that day ſhall haue done to you all the good that he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, and ſhal haue made you Kings and Queenes to raigne with him and his roiall Son for euer then it ſhal be no griefe nor offence of mind vnto you, that you haue not powred out your ſelues into all exceſſe of riot &amp; committed ſinne with greedineſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:21561:42"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21561:42"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21561:43"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21561:43"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21561:44"/> as the prophane and vngodlie doe. Then it ſhall not repent you that you haue conſecrated the flower of your youth to GOD, who is ſo bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a rewarder of them that ſeek him. What hurt ſhall it be then vnto you that you haue ſhu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned this luſt, &amp; that follie: this vice and that wantonnes, which you might haue committed, &amp; whereunto you haue beene tempted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what need you then ſtomack at it that you haue beene termed modeſt fooles and preciſians, and ſuch other names of diſgrace by the godleſſe multitude, whom you ſee damned by a iuſt ſentence, &amp; haled away to end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe torments before your face? where they ſhall beg that one of you may be ſent to dip but the tip of your finger in water, to coole their tongue in the middeſt of the flames, &amp; ſhall not obtaine it; who would not rather mourne for his ſinnes now, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them now, and change his courſe now, though it be with ſome vneaſe and wraſtling at the firſt, then to wiſh hee had done ſo afterward
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21561:44"/> when it is too late? and to lament and roare in that remedileſſe horrour and deſpaire for euer: bearing a part in that dolefull morning and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning muſicke of the wicked in Hell, <hi>We haue wearied our ſelues in the waies of wickednes and deſtruction,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Wiſd. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>and we haue gone thorow dangerous pathes, but we haue not knowne the waie of the Lord. What hath pride profited vs, or vvhat benefite hath the pompe of riches brought vs?</hi> All theſe things are paſſed away with a ſhadow, and as a poſt that ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth mainly by: we haue had the righteous in deriſion, and in a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of reproch: <hi>We fooles thought their life madnes,</hi> and their end without honour: But loe, they are counted among the children of GOD, and their portion is among the Saints. So haue we erred in our imaginations, and the ſunne of vndeſtanding hath not riſen vpon vs. Now wee know, when it hurts vs to know; now wee vnderſtand, when ignorance were a bleſſing. To conclude this Chapterr and this firſt part of my Treatiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:21561:45"/> whatſoeuer you haue beene in the yeares paſt, be new men now, I will not giue you reſpite till next yeare, nor next moneth, nor next morrow, but euen this day, this night, this houre in which thou art admoniſhed, amend: remember the name of the Lord is I AM for euer; and he likes notthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are alwaies, I wil be, repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance is neuer too ſoone, ſo long as the ſin is gone before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Youth</hi> is the Spring, <hi>Age</hi> is the Harueſt: in one we ſowe, in the other wee reape, if in our youth we ſowe the ſeed of vertue and obedience, we ſhall in our age reap the fruits of ioy, peace and perſeuerance to euerlaſting life, if the <hi>tares of vice and licentiouſnes,</hi> it will be hard if euer the harueſt bee other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnprofitable bu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dles, which will but kindle the vnquenceable fire of hell vpon our heades. Let your creation, or your redemption or vow in Baptiſme, or the power and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Lord, or the terrours of conſcience, or Gods reiecting of our praiers, or Chriſts denying you his
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21561:45"/> interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or the fighting of the crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures againſt you, or the Lords curſe vpon your bleſſings; or the hardening of your harts by cuſtome of ſin, or the vncertainty of your death, or the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of late repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance, or the baſe &amp; vnbeſeeming meaſure offred to God, or the increaſing of your accounts, or the ſtrictnes of the laſt iudgement, or hell fire it ſelfe, or all theſe together, rouſe and ſtartle you from your bed of ſloth, and cauſe you to reforme your liues renounce the world &amp; worldly wickednes, and to honour the Lord your God, or euer he take is light fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, &amp; or euer your feet ſtumble in the darke mountaines, leſt while you looke for the light he turn it into the blacknes of the ſhadow of death. But if you will not heare me that giue you ſeaſonable warning, my very heart ſhall mourne in ſecret for your ſtubbornnes, &amp; mine eyes ſhall weep and raine down teares, becauſe the Lords people are ſold vnto ſin, &amp; the children of my mother are caried captiue to deſtruction.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:21561:46"/>
            <head>THE SECOND PART.</head>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING ſpoken of the miſcheefes &amp; dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers which we ſtand liable to, ſo long as we are vnconuerted; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with me next the meanes which the Lord hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for our conuerſion; that if wee haue a mind of returning we may make vſe of them and not negligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paſſe them ouer without any fruit, as our faſhion hath beene in former times. Almightie GOD hath giuen vs firſt our life &amp; being in this world, he hath made vs men,<note place="margin">Gods be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits.</note> and breathed in vs a reaſonable ſoule, whereas whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the clay was in his hand, hee might
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21561:46"/> haue moulded vs into any other ſhape; hath giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs our ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes, &amp; diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted all our limmes, according to their proper and ſeuerall functions: he hath put all the creatures in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection vnder our feet: ſo that from the glorious Sunne in the firmament to the little Emmet that creepeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the duſt, euery thing doth vs ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. He hath preſerued vs hitherto all our life long from innumerable dangers, whereinto others haue fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and whereinto we had fallen if his gracious hand had not vpholden vs: And (which paſſeth all this) he hath by the death and ſufferings of his owne Son redeemed vs from the mouth of hel, into which elſe we eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mothers ſonne of vs irrecouerably were fallen. Now ſaith the Apoſtle, this bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifulnes of God leadeth vs to repentance. Therefore hath he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed all theſe benefits vpon vs, and promiſed many moe, thereby to ſtir vs vp to abandon vicious life, and to betake our ſelues to his holy &amp; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſeruice. <hi>Trie mee</hi> faith the Lord,<note place="margin">Mal. 3.10.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21561:47"/> whether I will not open the windows of heauen &amp; powre you out bleſſings without meaſure if you will returne vnto me.</p>
               <p>O my Brethren, if your hearts be not ſauage, how can it be but this kindnes of ſo great a Maieſty, ſhould binde vs to him for euer? what beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ingratitude is it to turne ſo many comforts and good things, as he hath giuen vs (that we might be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter able to ſerue him) to the diſhonor and iniury of ſo louing a giuer by vſing them to ſerue vs in ſinne? our dogs are not ſo vngratefull to their maſters; the Lions and Beares haue ſhewed more courteſie &amp; thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to their benefactors. That he hath ſpred our table with full di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, and made our cup to ouerflow; that he hath allowed vs warme clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by day, and a well fethered neſt to couch in at night, &amp; bodily health to make theſe things ſweeter and bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter taſted to vs, are bounties that we can neuer deſerue while we liue with all the obedience we are able
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21561:47"/> to performe. But that GOD for man ſhould become man, and that God for man ſhould die in the fleſh, and ſuſtaine ſo many ſhamefull indigni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties and intollerable paines in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing the worke of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption; this onely, this wholly &amp; this more then all things doth chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge vnto it euen by ſpeciall deſert, all our life, all our labour, all our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and al our loue. That a man fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giueth his goods to another, is a token of no ſmall bountie; but to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow his owne life for another, and that not for friends but for enemies, as the Sonne of God did, when he died for vs, it is an incomparable and an vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiueable bountie, the Angels of heauen do wonder at it, and deſire, (as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith) contiually to behold and looke into it: and ſurely if this bountie and gratiouſnes of our God, cannot win vs to cleanſe our waies and forſake our ſinnes, all the dewes of grace are quite and cleane dried vp in our hearts, and there is no hope that any thing will win vs. But it
<pb facs="tcp:21561:48"/> will fall out by vs, as <hi>Eſdras</hi> in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond booke and 9. chapter grauely denounceth againſt ſome like vs. <hi>Such as in their life haue receiued benefits from the Lord, and haue not regarded to know him; but haue abhorred his law whileſt they were yet in libertie, and when they had yet leiſure of amendment, and would not vnderſtand, but deſpiſed it: they muſt be taught after death by paine what it is, to recompence euill for good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another good meanes to bring vs to repentance is, the conſideration of Gods iudgements executed vpon ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in all ages, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath made examples for our admonition, on whom the ends of the worlde are come. The Angels for one ſinne were throwne out of heauen. <hi>Adam</hi> for one ſinne caſt out of Paradiſe, and all his poſterity after him condemned to perpetuall miſerie. <hi>Lots</hi> wife for one ſinne turned into a pillar of ſalt. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> for one ſinne debarred from entering the Land of Canaan. <hi>Michel</hi> for one ſinne plagued with barrenneſſe. The whole tribe of <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iamin</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:21561:48"/> for one ſin rooted out. Three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore &amp; tenne thouſand Iſraelites for one ſinne of <hi>Dauids,</hi> in three dayes conſumed with peſtilence. <hi>Ananias</hi> &amp; <hi>Sapphira</hi> for one ſtruck dead in the place. And yet thou after many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſinnes, crieſt ſtill God is merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and preſumeſt that thy part in that mercy will be as great as the thiefes vpon the Croſſe. <hi>God is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull,</hi> I deny it not: So the Phyſician is skilfull, and yet giues ouer his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſometimes, becauſe he ſees him to be incurable. If thou be damned, it is not becauſe the Lord wants mercie, but becauſe by deferring repentance thy heart is deaded, and thou art paſt recouerie. Tell me not of the thiefe vpon the Croſſe, for of two theeues one was damned. It was a miracle, and miracles were no miracles if they were common. All the Scriptures thorow there is not one ſuch another example to be found: and therefore for thee preſumptuouſly to goe on in thy ſins vpon this ſhaddow of hope, is all one, as if ſom good fellow ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:21561:49"/> hope his horſe would ſpeake Engliſh, becauſe once <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe vttered plainely the language of <hi>Moab.</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe be they that deſtroy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the workes of their owne hands (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) calling ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie vnto them both with hands &amp; words, &amp; when they think they haue a friend of it, they come to naught.</p>
               <p>But what ſhould I ſpeake of anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent iudgements, when thoſe that haue beene executed at our owne doores, haue not wrought vpon our hearts? To omit all other, what are wee the better for that dreadfull peſtilence ſo lately amongſt vs, when Death like a mercileſſe tyrant thruſt all out of doores both old and young before him, as if he would take poſſeſſion of our houſes one after another, till hee had ſeazed the whole Citie into his owne vſe? O my brethren, thoſe that be not blinde may ſee, there is not one ſinne leſſe this yeare, then was the laſt. In the Church there is as much careleſſneſſe and contempt of Gods word: In the ſtreetes as much
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21561:49"/> pride: In the ſhops as much lying and ſwearing: In the Tauernes as much drunkenneſſe and exceſſe (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding his Maieſties act of reſtraint) In other places as much filthineſſe, and as little conſcience and deuotion as euer there was before, ſo that the Lord may complaine of vs as he did of old: I haue ſmitten them, and they haue not ſorrowed; I haue corrected them for amendment, and they are worſe and worſe. The Lord grant we be not caſt off (as a father caſts off his vnthrifty ſonne, when no meanes will reclaime him) and that the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouing of his plague from vs (ſeeing wee are not bettered by it) be not a kinde of cruell pity: and a giuing vs vp to our owne hearts luſt till our iniquity be full, that wee may then fall by an vtter deſtruction, chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the meane time the countries round about vs, as hauing ſome hope: of their turning and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Let vs therefore with all ſpeed humble our ſelues vnder Gods migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:21561:50"/> hand, and make a godly vſe of his iudgments that euery litle chaſtiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his may driue vs to a lothing &amp; forſaking of our former euil waies; that we may ſtand in awe and not ſinne: for our God is a iealous God, and a conſuming fire, ſo ſhall he ſmel a ſauour of reſt, and receiue an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement for the land; ſo ſhall the light of his countenance be lifted vp vpon vs, and ſo ſhal it go well with vs and with our children after vs in their generations.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The word preached Gods Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</note>Another very direct meanes to this end, is the preaching of Gods word &amp; the voice of his Prophets &amp; mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, riſing vp early, &amp; premoniſhing vs of our da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, &amp; ſhewing vs the way wherin we ſhould walk. Therfore the Lord when he ſent the Prophet <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> to the people of Iſrael and Iuda, he bade him proclaime a faſt, and tell them what he had threatned againſt them:<note place="margin">Ier. 36.</note> Becauſe (ſaith the Lord) it may be when they heare the euill that I purpoſe to bring vpon them, they will returne from their wickedneſſe,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21561:50"/> and ſo by that meanes I may forgiue them their ſinnes, and receiue them to fauour. This is the <hi>manna that came downe from heauen,</hi> this is <hi>the immortall ſeed by which ſo many are borne to God.</hi> How great cauſe haue wee to bleſſe the Lord that it hath pleaſed him ſo to diſpoſe of vs, that wee ſhould be borne and bred in ſuch a time, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſuch a people, as profeſſe the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, and are daily taught and inſtructed both to beleeue and liue accordingly? Our Fathers longed to ſee theſe dayes, and could not ſee them; we feare no burning nor impriſonment for profeſſing the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, wee neede not croſſe the ſeas to ſeeke inſtruction, wee may in a bleſſed freedome of minde and body approch to Gods altars, <hi>and ſit at the feete of the Lords Prophets, and heare thoſe heauenly comforts and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from their mouthes. Neuer was London ſo well ſupplied with godly reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Miniſters, ſince the first ſtone of her walles was layd, then in this very day. The Lord Ieſus continue and encreaſe
<pb facs="tcp:21561:51"/> the number.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But what account make we of theſe meanes? we can content our ſelues to ſit an houre in the Church to heare Gods word taught, not for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence but for faſhion, as our deedes make plaine. For where almoſt is he or ſhe that hath left any one deere ſin this ſeauen yeares, though twice ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen yeares they haue heard it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned? nay, (which is ſtrange) vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the monday we commit thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſinnes which vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sabbath day before were to our faces moſt parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly reprooued, which were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to diſcourage vtterly thoſe men of God in the worke of their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie, they taking ſuch paines, wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching for vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſleep, ſtudying and ſpending their ſpirits to bring vs to repentance, and we (like wretches) making ſmall account of it, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiting little in godlineſſe by it: but that the Lord hath ſayd, his word ſhal neuer goe forth in vaine; but either it ſhall lift vs vp higher to his courts in heauen, or ſinke vs downe deeper
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21561:51"/> into the pit of hell. And the labours of his Miniſters ſhall be as highly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded for leauing the graceleſſe ones without excuſe, as for conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a weake ſoule from going aſtray.</p>
               <p>A Seruaunt when hee is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to do any thing by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, will feare to looke his Maſter in the face, or to come in his way if hee neglect it, and doe it not. How dare wee then hauing ſate in the Church, and there heard (out of the Pulpit the ſeate of Gods Oracles) ſin forbidden, repentance enioyned, our negligence taxed, not once, but continually from time to time, with precept vpon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, line vpon line: I ſay, how dare we preſſe ſo boldly without any awe or reuerence into the preſence of God (the great Maſter of all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in the world) Sabbath after Sab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bath, and yet guilty to our ſelues in the meane time of ſo great diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? vnleſſe wee come thither in an inſolent faſhion to ſtout and out-face the Lord; or to laugh in our ſleeues at his weakneſſe that will be borne in
<pb facs="tcp:21561:52"/> hand with a cunning ſemblance, and as well pleaſed as if the deede were performed.</p>
               <p>O my brethren, tremble to dally in this ſort with the Almighty: if hee ſpeake, let his ſeruants heare: if hee command, deferre not to doe it: receiue it not as the word of man, but as it is indeede the word of God. Pray aforehand that you may feele the vertue and power of it in your heart, renuing and changing your willes and affections: let the feete of them be beautifull that bring this ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of peace and good things vnto you: They are the Embaſſadours of the euerliuing God, and diſpoſers of his ſecrets: they are our Fathers in Chriſt, by whom wee are new begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to eternall life. The Lord hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them power out of his word to pronounce his ſentence, ſo that what they binde on earth is bound in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: and what they looſe on earth is looſed in heauen. Let vs haue them in ſingular loue &amp; reuerence for their works ſake. The contempt of their
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21561:52"/> perſons is a notable policie of the diuell, to make their teaching be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned alſo. Let vs ſhew our thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to God for them, in obeying thoſe things which they command vs in his name. They haue called vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs long enough for amendment; let them now haue cauſe to commend vs that wee haue amended. Let our hearing be at length a ioy to them, leſt their ſorrow be hereafter a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt vs: One <hi>Ionah</hi> conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Niniueh, what a ſhame is it to vs that ſo many <hi>Ionahs</hi> ſhould doe no good in London?</p>
               <p>Another meanes to ſet vs forward in the way of repentance,<note place="margin">Good bookes &amp; conference.</note> is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of good bookes, &amp; mutuall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, and exhortation one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Theſe doe both after one ſort bob vs continually on the elbowe, and euen importune vs to well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and would worke ſome good ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect if we were not negligent &amp; care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in the vſing of them. But ſo it is, how much time doe we ſpend idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in doing nothing, or vnthriftily in
<pb facs="tcp:21561:53"/> doing naught, neuer taking a good booke in our hands all the weeke long, though we haue choice of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and our trades will beare it; or if wee begin, it growes irkſom ſtraight before wee haue turned one leafe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer; or if we haue the patience to goe thorow to the end (ſlightly enough;) wee caſt it in a corner to be moulded and moath-eaten, and are as much the better as he that hath lookt in a glaſſe is, after his backe is turned: becauſe we doe not ſtirre vp and whet our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance by a ſecond more aduiſed reading, eſteeming our olde bookes as olde friends, which muſt euer now and then be viſited, that acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance may be renewed and not loſt.</p>
               <p>So for our mutuall exhorting one another, how vnequally haue we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed it? ſparing them too much with whom we are inward; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouing them too tartly who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we like not ſo well: and perhaps thinking ſcorne to be admoniſhed our ſelues by any. How many times when we haue met together for our comforts,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21561:53"/> and to the edifying one of another in godlineſſe, haue wee burſt out into prophane and idle talke, letting our mouth looſe to all vanity, that ſhould haue vttered gracious words, giuing proofe of the inward ſanctification of our hearts: ſo ſlie is the diuel (the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual enemie of all good things) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wee goe about to diminiſh his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; to rob vs from our ſelues, and diuert our beſt thoughts another way. I ſpeake this the rather, that all thoſe that are the profeſſors of the Goſpell, might vſe theſe means here after with more care and conſcience, leſt they be ouer-reacht by this ſlight of Sathan: and ſet a watch before their mouth, and keepe the doore of their lips, that they giue no example of lightneſſe or vanity to them that are new conuerts, nor vnto any other: but carying the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues as paterns vnto them, in word, in conuerſation, in faith, in ſpirit, in loue and in pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that euen thoſe that are back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardeſt in religion, may be drawne by their integrity to repentance from
<pb facs="tcp:21561:54"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:21561:54"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21561:55"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:21561:55"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21561:56"/> the corruptions of the world. For vertue ſhewes ſo well in whomſoeuer it is, that it ſtirres vp a meruailous loue and deſire of it in them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it.</p>
               <p>But if neither Gods benefits, nor his iudgements, nor his word, nor godly bookes, nor the good counſell and admonition and examples of our brethren (who are more carefull of our ſaluation then we our ſelues) will preuaile with vs, let the ſhortnes and vncertainty of our owne life make vs looke about vs. For what is our life but a vapour, a flower, a flaſh, a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, a dreame, vanity, nothing? Haue you euer obſerued the bubbles which boyes blow vp in a ſhell of ſope-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, how ſome being ſwollen to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate quantity, breake immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly in the ſhell? ſome the wind whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vp aloft into the aire, and are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued there: ſome flie alowe by ground, till at length they daſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ground, and come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Such things are men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, when you ſee a thouſand of them
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21561:56"/> walking the ſtreetes, imagine you ſee a thouſand belles or bubbles of water wandering vp and downe: ſome a high aboue all their fellowes (as the gale fauours them) ſome in a lower region, and with a thought as high as the higheſt: ſome beneath that lownes, and ſome as low as the paue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Now ſtand ſtill a little and marke them, and you ſhall ſee ſome times one ſtriking out another, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times tenne, or twenty, or thirty pop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping out of themſelues, and inſtantly ſo many more (ſome of the higheſt, ſome of the loweſt, ſome of the meane ones one amongſt another) ſo that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non you cannot ſee one of the olde men or bubbles left, but all are new men or new bubbles (call them which you will, for all is one) blowne vp in the places of the former.</p>
               <p>If this be our beſt firmeneſſe, if our mettall be thus full of flawes, if our life be but a moment, and yet vpon that moment depends eternitie of weale or woe in the life to come: who would not take opportunitie by the
<pb facs="tcp:21561:57"/> foretop, and make hay (as the ſaying is) while the ſunne ſhines? who would put off his amendment till to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, when he knowes not what a day may bring forth? Man knoweth not his end (ſaith the wiſeſt among men) but euen as the fiſhes be taken with the hooke, and the birdes be ſodainly intrapped with the ſnate, ſo are the children of men preuented with the euill day when it comes vpon them ſodainly.</p>
               <p>When the tree falleth, whether to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the North or South, there it li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: and in the ſame ſtate you die, you ſhall be iudged. Learne therefore to number your dayes, and conſider ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly of your latter end, that you may repent betimes, for that is wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and depart from euill, for that is vnderſtanding. Or if you ſcorne all other ſchoole-maſters, learne of the diuell one rule of policy; He kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing his time to be ſhort, will doe what miſchiefe he can, you knowing your time to be ſhort, doe you what good you can.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:21561:57"/>
               <head>CHAP. 6</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here remaines yet three o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means, which I cannot ouerpaſſe without making mention of them.</p>
               <p>The firſt is the care of maſters,<note place="margin">Godly carefull Maſters.</note> and the diſcipline of a well gouerned houſe, which may ſet ſtraight the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners of a yong man, and reſtraine him from thoſe vices, whereto by reaſon of his age, or the corruption of the place, he is inclined: For the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe holdeth for the moſt part true; LIKE MASTER, LIKE MAN. If <hi>Abraham</hi> feare God, his ſeruants and houſhold will bee religious. If <hi>Herod</hi> ſcorne Chriſt, his captaines &amp; courtiers wil deride him alſo. In the Hiſtory of the Apoſtles Acts, when any houſholder was conuerted to the faith of Chriſt, you ſhall finde it ſaid;
<pb facs="tcp:21561:58"/> 
                  <hi>The man beleeued and all his houſhold,</hi> ſhewing, that as they were ſwaied be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of an Idolatrous maſter, to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition: ſo now they are ſwaied by a Chriſtian maſter to the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſeruice of God.</p>
               <p>Here therefore I thinke it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe to ſhew the duty of a Maſter in ſome meaſure as God ſhal enable me; not that I would take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me to teach my elders and betters (yet let none diſdaine to learne of yong ones, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euen our cradle ſometimes may teach vs wiſedome; for out of the mouthes of babes and ſucklings hath the Lord ordained ſtrength) but to the end that we that are yet ſeruants and prentiſes may know how to cary and behaue our ſelues, when it ſhall pleaſe the Lord, to lay ſuch a charge vpon vs.</p>
               <p>Firſt, (my Brethren) when the Lord ſhall call vs to this waightie charge, that we come to be rulers of families, and that we keep ſeruants, it behooueth vs, nay, we are bound in duty to God, to haue as great a care
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21561:58"/> of their ſaluation as of our owne, and to ſee they do their faithfull ſeruice to God, as we will looke that they ſhould faithfully ſerue vs: For aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly that ſeruant that is not faithfull to GOD, can neuer bee faithfull to his maſter; but he that ſerues GOD with a good conſcience, wil ſerue his maſter with a good conſcience. The awe &amp; preſence of his maſter to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eie and chide him needes not, for his owne heart will check him,<note place="margin">They doe beſt ſerue their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, that haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned firſt to ſerue God.</note> and the feare of God will keep him from vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſtines. You may find a kind of pick-thanke officiouſnes in ſeruants of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther making; but there is no ſeruice like his that ſerues man for conſcience toward God.</p>
               <p>And beſide our duty to God, and deſire of faithful ſeruice to our ſelues, the care we ſhould haue of our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens godly education, that they be not corrupted, ſhold double our care to keep godly ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: for the liberal diſpoſition of a child is eaſily ſpilt with the leaud manners of a ſeruant. Hence it commeth that almoſt their
<pb facs="tcp:21561:59"/> firſt words are ribauldrie and feareful othes, and that they learne to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme God before they can plainely ſpeake GOD; yea ſometime they proue twofold more the children of Satan then their Tutors were: For a new veſſell will keep the tatch of the firſt ſeaſoning a long time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>Cauſe them therefore to frequent the holy exerciſe of religion, as Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, Catechiſing, Praier, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments &amp;c. Bring them with you, where they may be inſtructed in the waies of the Lord to doe righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, eſpecially on the Sabbath day: becauſe that is a day appointed and ſet apart of God himſelfe for his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſeruice, wherein he wil haue our ſeruant as free as our ſelues, and to the end we may prepare them the better to the ſanctifying of the Lords day, we are to call them vp betimes in the morning, to praier, wherein firſt we are to thanke the Lord, for all his mercies to ſuch vnworthy wretches, and namely for the reſt and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21561:59"/> preſeruation the night paſt: Then to beſeech his Maieſtie that hee would ſo prepare and fit our hearts to the profitable retaining of his moſt holy and bleſſed word, and ſo direct the mouthes of his miniſters that day in the vttering of it, that it may be a comfortable ſauour of life and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to vs, and not a ſauour of death vnto deſtruction.</p>
               <p>And hauing ended this duty by 7. in the morning, we may if wee will directly goe where there ſhall bee a Sermon vntill eight ſo comming home we are to goe to our owne Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church, both in the forenoone, and in the afternoone; and after that to ſome Lecture as there be diuers (bleſſed bee GOD) in diuers parts of the City. And hauing thus ſpent the day till ſix at night, we are not to content our ſelues there, thinking we haue done by this time a work of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererogation; but to come directly from the Lecture to our houſes, and call our ſeruants together, to praiers to almighty God, that it would pleaſe
<pb facs="tcp:21561:60"/> his Maieſtie to giue a bleſſing vpon that which we haue heard, that wee may auoide the ſinnes, execute the good duties, feare the threatnings, and lay vp the comforts from the mouth of his miniſters plainely ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed and laid down vnto vs. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ended praiers for that inſtant, we are to examine euery one of them particularly what leſſons they haue learned at Church, and what vſes they were taught of thoſe leſſons: and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing done that, to giue them a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall exhortation, incouraging them to goe forward in godlineſſe, which hath promiſes of this life, and of that which is to come, and ſo to make an end for that time, with ſinging a Pſalm of thankeſgiuing.</p>
               <p>NOW as we are to performe theſe duties on the Sabbath day, ſo we haue our duties to performe on the weeke daies alſo: For it is not enough for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man to giue his family victuals, and prouiſion one day in the weeke, and let them faſt all the reſt of the weeke after, for ſo he ſhould ſoone
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21561:60"/> make a leane houſhold; but we muſt deale with our ſeruants in Spiritual things, as we deale with them in Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall things; that is, as wee allow them meat and drinke ſufficiently all the weeke daies, and on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day they haue extraordinary diſhes: So although we haue beene carefull to pray and inſtruct them in religion on the Sabbath day: yet we muſt looke we do our duties in the weeke daies alſo, although not like vnto the Sabbath: for the Lord doth not require it at our hands. This diſcipline and good order if wee would carefully inure our Prentiſes to, ſeuen or eight yeares together till their firſt youth (the age which is ſet vpon the very pinacle of temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) be paſt ouer, methinkes it were enough to kill all the weedes of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in them, &amp; to make euen Atheiſts religious, and grow into a habit of ſanctimony and godlineſſe.</p>
               <p>Here I thinke it needfull for euery one of vs, (as we are yet ſeruants) to know our duties alſo; that wee may
<pb facs="tcp:21561:61"/> demeane our ſelues, agreeably to our preſent condition.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Seruants duty.</note>Firſt then wee are to follow the counſel of the Apoſtle, to be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient vnto our bodily maſters with feare and trembling, becauſe they be (in their places) vnto vs as God, God hath ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ouer vs in his own ſtead; and therefore we ought not onely to carry a reuerend eſtimation of them, counting them worthy of all honor, but to performe our duty and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice vnto them, not to the eie as men pleaſers, but as the ſeruants of Chriſt, doing the will of God himſelfe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glie and from the heart, labouring continually to pleaſe them, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting our ſelues to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in all things, as the holy Ghoſt commandeth. But this muſt not be vnderſtood abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but with an exception; <hi>So they bee lawfull things.</hi> For if a maſter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand his ſeruant to ſpeake a lie, or to ſweare his commodities coſt ſo much, when they coſt much leſſe, or to breake the Lords Sabbath; in ſuch a caſe we ought rather to obey God
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21561:61"/> then man: but in all iuſt and lawfull impoſitions (not croſſing their roiall commandement) we are to conforme our ſelues in all duty and obedience to them, yea not only to the good and courteous, but euen to the froward &amp; ſower. For this is thankworthy, ſaith Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> if a ſeruant for conſcience toward GOD endure ſmart, ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring wrongfully. But it is a great fault in vs that are ſeruants, that if correction be giuen vs (though with iuſtice and diſcretion) we will ſay moſt commonly wee deſerue it not. This is not the ſaying of the holy Ghoſt: For (ſaith he) what praiſe is it for a ſeruant to be buffeted for his faults? but and if yee fault not, and yet ſuffer hard vſage and take it pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, then is there thanke with God. And herein what better ſatisfaction or quieting of our mindes can we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, then the example of our Sauiour himſelfe, who neuer ſinned, neither was there guile found in his mouth, yet he was reuiled, and reuiled not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, he ſuffered beyond all degrees
<pb facs="tcp:21561:62"/> of patience, &amp; opened not his mouth; but committed reuenge to him that iudgeth righteouſly, euen to God his Father: So ought wee (my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) when our maſters bee out of reaſon, and offer vs extreame mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to put it vp and endure it pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, knowing that they alſo haue a maſter in Heauen, who beholdeth with an equall eie both vs and them; and not to anſwer, Sir I deſerue it not: For if correction ſhould not bee giuen to the moſt of vs till wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe we deſerue it, it ſhould neuer be giuen vs.</p>
               <p>Heere I cannot keepe ſilence, but I muſt needes make known how good and gratious the Lord hath ſhewed himſelfe in this caſe to mee his moſt vnworthy ſeruant, and the rather to cauſe all other Prentiſes to thinke themſelues not miſerable but moſt happy, when the Lord hath ſet ouer them ſuch matters, as giue them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued correction with wiſedome &amp; diſcretion: For certainly (my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) had not I had ſuch a maſter,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21561:62"/> (whoſe care and diligence hath beene ſo great ouer me, in reſtraining mee from that ſcope &amp; liberty, which my wretched and vntamed nature did deſire) it had beene better a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times I had neuer beene borne: For my bringing vp from my child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, vntill the time I came to my maſter, was moſt miſerable and wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, by reaſon of my ſinnes and the ignorance wherein I liued, as the caſe of too too many is in theſe daies: yea and ſince I came to be a Prentiſe (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till of late time) my life was moſt odious and abominable both in the ſight of GOD and Man. But bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed bee the name of the Lord, who hath giuen me a good maſter, to hold me backe, that I could not be ſo wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked as I would, and hath now alſo in ſome meaſure opened mine eies, (which haue beene a long time kept ſhut) that I might ſee how to wind my feet out of the ſnare of Satan.</p>
               <p>Therefore my deere Brethren (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all thoſe I ſpeake that deſire to bee partakers of the heauenly ioyes in
<pb facs="tcp:21561:63"/> the life to come) ſhew yourſelues o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient to your maſters, and ſubmit your ſelues vnder the yoake, yea al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it bee irkſome to the fleſh: for you knowe nor the great profit and rewarde that commeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vngodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Prentiſes.</note>But certainly (in griefe I ſpeake it) Prentiſes for the moſt part were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo leaudly and ſo wickedly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, neuer ſo vaine and ſo licentious, neuer ſo full of ſcoffing and deriſion, neuer ſo inſolent and contemptuous of God and good men, as they be in theſe dayes. For we are ſo apt to be corrupted, and (being corrupted) to corrupt, partly by reaſon of our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and partly of the place, that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe our Maſters be the more circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect in bringing of vs vp, the ſoules of many thouſand Prentiſes will be required at their hands; impunitie boldening vs in ſinne, and ſinne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully hardening our hearts, that all thought of repentance is put away from vs; or if any ſhall friendly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member vs, his beſt thanke is a mock
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21561:63"/> for his labour. When inquiſition ſhall be made for bloud of ſoules, I would euery one could ſtand forth, &amp; ſay, <hi>Not guiltie,</hi> but the Prentiſes themſelues. But I feare greatly that the Maſters will be to blame in that day alſo, and be put to their ſhifts for a currant anſwer, when they ſhall find none.</p>
               <p>For (without offence to any man, I will ſpeake a little) where is that Maſter almoſt that queſtions with his ſeruants about any religion at all? It may be ſometimes he will ſend them to Church; but when they returne, what doth he aske them of their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or profiting there? vnleſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps once at the hundreds end hee vouchſafe to knowe the chapter and verſe of the Text, which (betweene the Church-doore and home) euen a Parrot wold be taught to pronounce. Let him ſend any of his people of ſome worldly buſineſſe, and hee will be ſure to aske him how he ſped, and nothing will he leaue vnasked to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the effect of the errand hee
<pb facs="tcp:21561:64"/> ſent him about: but for Gods buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſoule matters be they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed negligently, or not done at all, it mattereth not; he is ſure no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count will be required of any ſuch thing all the time of his prentiſhip. And this is the reaſon that ſeruants depart as ignorant after they haue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſeuen or eight yeares ſeruice, as they were when they came firſt (not of their trades) I meane of that which is more worth then all the trades in the worlde. For a man ſhall profit much to know God. The true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God will bring more ſound profit in one day to a man, then the beſt trade in London will doe in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen yeares. For godlineſſe is profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto all things (ſaith the Apoſtle) as hauing the bleſſings of this life, and of that which is to come.</p>
               <p>Howbeit, ſome there be in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don that I knowe (and more I doubt not that I knowe not) which vſe good orders in their houſes, to the generall good of their families (and I deſire the Lord to increaſe their number)
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21561:64"/> But a hundred to one neuer ſpent any time with their ſeruants, in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of religion, no not ſo much as to call them to prayers either morning or euening once in a yeare, whereas they are bound (in duty to God) to do it euery morning &amp; euening; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there were no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement from God, nor preſident in this kind, yet very neceſſity and the ſloth of youth ſhould co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtraine vs; &amp; ſurely if maſters would care as they ſhould, to traine vp their houſholds in the feare of god, &amp; in the practiſe of good things it could not be that London ſhould harbor ſo many vngodly Pre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes, or that diuers men ſhold co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plain (as they do) of ſeruants leaudnes, that they cannot thriue in the world; for they haue good meanes of getting, but is ſpent they cannot tell how ſo ſoone as it is gotten: Alas, how can it be any otherwiſe? if their ſeruants be not taught the feare of GOD, and to keep a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, how is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible that euer they ſhould haue any true ſeruice at their hands?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21561:65"/>
               <p>But ſome will ſay againe, this is not ſo: for by experience I can ſpeake this of a truth, that for mine own part I neuer inſtructed my folks in all my life in any religion at all: No, I neuer heard them ſo much as to read a chapter, and yet I thanke God, he hath bleſſed me with good ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. For I finde my riches to increaſe, and I thriue well, and therefore it is not the bringing of them vp in religion, that makes a man come forward in the world; but if his fortune be good, wealth with come on.</p>
               <p>Fortune? no, no, it is the great handy work of GOD in ſome mens ſeruants, that hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe, and ſeeke more for ſaluation then their maſters be aware of, (or elſe their poore ſoules might be caſt away and periſh for euer) and then who knowes not that ſuch a man thriues for his ſeruants ſake, as <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> did for <hi>Iacobs,</hi> and as <hi>Potiphar</hi> did for <hi>Ioſephs?</hi> Or it may be, GOD caſts his bleſſings into thy lap (euen againſt all meanes) to ſtirre thee vp
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21561:65"/> to greater thankfulneſſe and care to ſerue him afterwards, or elſe to leaue thee the more vnexcuſable in his great iudgement for not performing ſuch duty and ſeruice.</p>
               <p>And therefore let none caſt ſurmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of excuſe to colour or ſhift out the matter any longer, but wherein it appeareth to your owne conſciences, you haue beene negligent, make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends with more care hereafter: aske not which of your neighbours doth thus and thus, and if they do it not, you meane not to begin. But reſolue you with <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> let others take what courſe they will, <hi>I and my houſe will ſerue the Lord.</hi> Let your people ſee you going before them in the practiſe of euery good thing, and in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horring and auoiding of euill, ſo ſhal they firſt feare to doe that which you hate, and at length fall in loue with that which you practiſe. It ſhall get you more authority and reſpect with them heere, and increaſe the bleſſednes of your own ſoules another day, that you haue been the meanes
<pb facs="tcp:21561:66"/> (through the bleſſing of God) to ſaue your poore prentiſes ſoules alſo.</p>
               <p>And heere I ſhall deſire my wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful maſters of this City (to whoſe ſight this little ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dfull of papers may come) not to take offence at any thing I haue ſpoken out of zeale and heartie meaning, nor to impute it to arrogancie in me, that I haue inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medled in their offices (From which proud ſin (I thank my God) I am free) but if it be iuſt that I haue ſaied, and agreeable to Gods word, that they will not diſdaine to do it, it ſhall not only be no diſparagement, but praiſe and honor to them, comfort to other of Gods children, and ioy to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, in heauen, that by their religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous care, their ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are made Gods ſeruants with them, and there is ſuch a towardly and hopefull ſucceſſion to ſtand vp after them, that as the Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians were examples of godlines to thoſe of Macedonia: ſo Londoners at length may be like exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp; religiouſnes to all the neighbor townes of <hi>Great Britaine</hi> alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:21561:66"/>
               <head>CHAP. 7.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He next good meanes to waken vs out of the ſleepe of ſinne, and to quicken vs to a new co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, is the ſweete conſolation and ioy which God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs in our ſoules and conſciences of his ſeruice, after we haue once made our peace with him by ſound and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable repentance. This is the peace that paſſeth all vnderſtanding; this is the earneſt of our inheritance; this is a preſent taſte or ſay of the ioyes of the life to come. I knowe my words ſeeme to the carnall and vnregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate a fained thing, as the womens report of Chriſts reſurrection did at firſt to the Diſciples; but if thou wouldſt doe as they did, neuer leaue till in thine owne perſon thou haſt tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:21561:67"/> out the truth of this matter, thou ſhouldeſt feele within thee ſuch a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe of ſweetneſſe, as thou thy ſelfe were not able to vtter. Thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſee with what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fortable cheere Chriſt would offer himſelf vnto thee; with what delicates he would refreſh thy ſoule; what ſecret affections hee would inſpire into thee; and with how pleaſant a cup of loue he would make thee merrie, if thou wouldſt follow his pathes, forſaking the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes of ſinne and worldly vanities. The leaſt drop of this diuine ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, would vtterly diſtaſt vnto thee all the pleaſures of ſinne, that euen the remembrance of them would be irkſome and vnſauorie.</p>
               <p>For mine owne part, I haue had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of this which I ſay. For (to my ſhame I ſpeake it) I haue beene as leaud and as wicked a fellow as euer thou haſt beene whoſoeuer thou art: and one that hath made as ſmall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of ſinning againſt God as euer thou haſt done, either in ſwearing, or lying, or prophaning the Lords Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21561:67"/> or in deriding the deere Saints and ſeruants of God. Nay, what vice would I haue left vnpractiſed, if I might haue come to the knowledge of it? what pleaſure, or vanitie, or abomination can be named, whereof I would not haue had, not a dram or ſip, but a drunken carouſe, if the Lord by good meanes had not reſtrained me from ſuch effuſion of beaſtlineſſe? It irketh me to thinke in what a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſtate I liued at that time: for had not God beene very mercifull vnto me, the earth might haue opened, and ſwallowed me vp quick for rebelling againſt his great Maieſtie, being Lord of heauen and earth: but ſuch was his goodneſſe to ſpare me, and ſuch was his patience, to waite for my repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: for euer magnified be his holy name therefore.</p>
               <p>For this cauſe, when once it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Maieſtie (in ſome meaſure) to giue mee a ſight and feeling of my ſinnes, through the preaching of his word (which I had a long time heard in vaine before) as alſo by meanes of
<pb facs="tcp:21561:68"/> ſome of my Brethren in Chriſt Ieſus, ſtirring mee vp continually with ſuch like admonitions as I doe now ſtirre vp thee, I conſulted not with fleſh &amp; bloud, but preſently ſet my ſelfe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt my former euill inclinations, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluing and endeuouring euery day to change the tenor of my life, and to ſerue God in better manner then euer I had done before, giuing ſmall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard what the companions of my leaudneſſe, and other of the prophane multitude did ſay of me, nor what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riding termes they beſtowed vpon men: for I ſaw no other way but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I muſt be a hell-hound, or be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>Puritan.</hi> And therefore I choſe rather to ſuffer reproch with the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, and to abide the name of hypocrite and diſſembler, &amp;c. then to be a varlet with euery varlet, or accounted an honeſt fellow amongſt the prophane. And ſo continuing in this courſe, and framing my ſelfe to liue more &amp; more in the feare of God, ſhaking off my olde ſinnes, I felt in my ſelfe in ſhort time ſuch a ſweete
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21561:68"/> and comfortable change, and ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall heauenly ioy of Gods ſeruice, that I would not haue exchanged it againe for all the choiceſt delights of the world heaped at once vpon my heart. And ſurely, my Brother, if thou wouldeſt once enter into this reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (as I haue done) turning from dead works to ſerue the liuing God; thou ſhouldeſt ſee what a banquet of celeſtiall delicates hee would ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, and how plentifully hee would powre forth the wine of his conſolations vnto thee, that thou mighteſt ſay, as <hi>Iudith</hi> did in another caſe: <hi>I will drinke now freely O my Lord;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudith 12.18.</note> becauſe <hi>my heart is merrie this day more then euer it was in all my life before.</hi> On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for this ſhalt thou feele ſorrow, that thou hadſt not ſooner embraced the meanes of thy conuerſion, that the ſooner thou mightſt haue beene par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of this diuine ioy, and theſe ſoules rauiſhing comforts.</p>
               <p>The laſt meanes I will ſpeake of, is, the conſideration of the ioyes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, whereof the ioy of Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb facs="tcp:21561:69"/> here is but a little drop or ſpark: that heauen the conſummation, perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or euerlaſting well-head of all pleaſures that can be ſeene, named or conceiued: ſeene, named, or concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, ſaid I? nay, no eye hath ſeene, no eare hath heard, no thought hath euer comprehended the ioy, the pleaſure the felicity, the glory which GOD hath layed vp in the life eternall for them that ſerue him, with an vpright heart in this world. The Scriptures doe ſometimes reſemble heauen to a Paradiſe or pleaſant field; ſometimes they deſcribe it by a goodly Citie; ſometimes by a Kings Court; but what are theſe but worldly deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that which paſſeth all the world? Go out into the moſt delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full parts of the Country, view the faire hilles, the flowrie vallies, the cryſtall fountaines, the cleere riuers, ſweet woods goodly plaines, variety of fruites, melody of birds &amp;c. and all this is nothing to it. Goe into the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſuruay the ſtately gates, firme walles, beautiful edifices, neat ſtreets,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21561:69"/> rich houſhold ſtuffe, all the deſirable things in the warehouſes and Cheſts of Merchants, Goldſmiths, Iewellers. &amp;c. and all theſe are nothing to it. Goe into the Court, note the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſuters, traine of attendants; magnificent feaſts, pompous ſeruice, muſical Inſtruments faire Ladies, gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering Courtiers, maskes, reuels all the pleaſures of a King; and all theſe are nothing to it. Let the beſt wit in the world beſtow his vtmoſt skill to ſet out all the delights and pleaſures of the ſonnes of men in their liuelieſt colours, yet all his expence of orato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie will ſcarſe giue you a glimpſe of this. Rack your owne thoughts vpon the tenters, ſhape out in your conceit a thouſand formes of pleaſure, yet all theſe are ſcarſe a ſhadow of it. And thinke what a kinde of bliſſe that is which paſſeth all companion, all vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance, all conceite of the wiſeſt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane heart. Neither is this for a day, or a moneth, or for terme of yeares, but an euerlaſting ſtate of bleſſednes, vndeterminable ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as God is God,
<pb facs="tcp:21561:70"/> and that is world without end; wee want a word to expreſſe it. And ſhall wee let ſlip ſuch a booty through our negligence, or wilfulneſſe, or ſloth, or inconſideratenes?</p>
               <p>If wee doe careleſly ouergoe but a good bargain in our ordinarie trades, which might yeeld vs a few crownes profit, how doth it vexe and chafe vs afterward? and doe we thinke ſuch a loſſe as this will be borne with eaſe if wee once ouergoe it, when it might earſt haue beene had for ſo little time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paines? Beleeue me, my Brother, the onely loſſe of heauen to a ſoule able to apprehend the loſſe, is a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient hell, if the Lord had appointed no other torment for euill doers.</p>
               <p>Come, come, ſtand no longer in thine owne light, ſee thy good, and take it. Why wilt thou let ſlip the opportunitie which nothing in the world can purchaſe thee againe? Why ſhouldeſt thou not euen in this houre change thy life, and make an end of wilfull ſinning againſt the Lord? Is it for that thou art loth to forgoe thy
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21561:70"/> olde delights, thy pleaſant compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and boon ſocieties? alas, what are thoſe ſliding baſe delights to the ſolide and noble delights I ſpake of euen now? or thy earthly fellowſhips, to the ſocietie of Angels and heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirits? Is it for that the wayes of godlineſſe are hard and painfull, and laborious? Is not the enioying of a Kingdome a good ſalue for that ſore? ſurely if all the paines and labours of all men in the world were layed vpon thy ſhoulders; if all thy life were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but weeping and lamentation like <hi>Ezekiels booke:</hi> nay, if thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt for a time endure hell fire it ſelfe, that afterward when Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth in his glory, thou mightſt be reckoned among his Saints, and enioy the heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of his choſen children; yet were not all thy paines and ſufferings wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be ballanced with the partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of ſuch an infinite &amp; vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able waight of glory. But to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing euery thing is an excuſe. For the ſeruice of God is eaſie, &amp; his yoke is ſweet. I will runne the way of thy
<pb facs="tcp:21561:71"/> commandements (ſaith the kingly Prophet) when thou ſhalt enlarge my heart. And againe; My delight is in thy commandements: yea they are the ioy and reioycing of my heart.</p>
               <p>What doeſt thou feare leſt thou ſholdſt fal away again after thou haſt bin once inlightned, that there can be no more renuing by repentance; &amp; ſo thy laſt end ſhould be worſe then thy beginning? care thou by making thine election ſure by good workes, pray vnto the Lord for his ſtrength and aſſiſtance, and feare not this feare, for it will bee as impoſſible for thee (being once regenerate and made the child of GOD) to fall finally away from godlineſſe, as it was for <hi>Ieremy</hi> to hold his peace (notwithſtanding his reſolution of ſilence) when the word of the Lord was as fire or gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder in his heart.</p>
               <p>Doeſt thou doubt whether God wil performe his promiſe? then ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer take vpon thee the name of a Chriſtian, he renders vengeance to the vngodly, why ſhould we doubt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21561:71"/> whether he will recompence and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward weldoers? Thou ſhalt heare thouſands complaine of the falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and faithleſneſſe of the world, whom thou truſteſt; if any haue complained of Gods ſlackneſſe, God hath driuen him out of his owne proofe anon after to recant, and to ſay with the Prophet, <hi>This is my weaknes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doeſt thou feare the reproch of nicknames and ignominious termes, which the new conuerted children of GOD do alwaies light on? art thou ſo without heart, and ſo very a coward, to be blowne from thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion with the breath of a prophane mouth? haddeſt thou rather keepe credit with the world and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell by weltring in ſinne, then ſerue GOD after the way which is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted diſcreditfull by the godleſſe of the world? A generous horſe though twenty curres come out barking and ſnarling at his heeles, as he trotteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the ſtreete, keepeth on his pace without ſo much as looking backe at
<pb facs="tcp:21561:72"/> them. So when theſe barkers of Gods ſeruants, and deriders of religion and good things, ſtep forth againſt thee, to hinder thee in thy courſe of a new conuerſation; let the height of thy mind diſdaine to regard them, or take notice of them; thinke they are but the Diuels ban dogs, hiſſed on by him to make thee breake thy pace in the waies of godlineſſe; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſo much the more couragiouſly goe on, that they may ſee how much they are deſpiſed.</p>
               <p>If all this cannot moue vs, we haue hard and fooliſh hearts; and I can ſay no more but we may go forward in our ſotted courſe, til we reap the fruit of our ouer weening. But I hope bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things of you (my brethren) and ſuch things as accompany the feare of God and ſaluation, though I thus ſpeake: Suffer not (I beſeech you for Chriſt Ieſus ſake) my hope to bee in vaine.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:21561:72"/>
            <head>THE THIRD PART.</head>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 8</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>ERE methinkes I heare ſome ſay, whoſe willes and affections the Lord hath begun to renue and change, whom yet Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would wrap about with the cords of their owne frailty; I would faine repent, but I cannot: my faith is ſo weake, and my heart ſo hard that I cannot be ſory for my ſinnes as I would.</p>
               <p>This is a ſweet ſaying (my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren:) For what can a man haue more then to feele his wants? for otherwiſe how ſhould we hunger &amp; thirſt after righteouſneſſe: and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly, he that hungers thus ſhall be ſatisfied, for the Lord that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what we want better then we our ſelues, lookes not ſo much to the outward ſhew of repentance, as to
<pb facs="tcp:21561:73"/> the inward affections of the heart, which are as actions in his ſight: and though our faith and repentance bee but weake, yet let vs know this aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly, that the Lord looketh more on the quality, then on the quantitie. Is a weake faith no faith, is a weake re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance no repentance? nay,</p>
               <p>The deſire of reconciliation with God in Chriſt (ſaith a godly writer of our time) is reconciliation it ſelfe: the deſire to beleeue is faith indeed: and the deſire to repent (in a touched heart) is repentance it ſelfe, not in the owne nature, but in Gods accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: For if wee being touched througly for our ſinnes, do deſire to haue them pardoned and to bee at one with GOD; GOD accepts vs as reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled. Only our deſire of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciliation muſt not be a flaſh but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued. Secondly, erneſt &amp; ſerious, though not alwaies alike, yet at ſometimes ſo, that we may ſay with the Prophet <hi>Dauid; My ſoule deſireth thee, O Lord, as the thirſty land deſireth raine, or the chaſed Hart the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21561:73"/> riuers of water.</hi> Thirdly, it muſt be in a touched heart: for when a man is touched in conſcience, the heart is caſt downe. (and as much as it can) it withdrawes it ſelfe from GOD: For this cauſe if then there bee any ſpirituall motions whereby the heart is lift vp vnto GOD, they are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt from the ſpirit of GOD. So then, though as yet thou want firme and liuely grace, yet art thou not altogether void of grace, if thou canſt vnſainedly deſire it, thy deſire is the ſeed, conception or bud of that which thou wanteſt. Now is the ſpring time of the ingrafted word, or the immortal ſeed caſt into the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of thy heart; wait but a while, vſing the good meanes to this end ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and thou ſhalt ſee the leaues, bloſſomes, and fruit will ſhortly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after. <hi>Thus fare he.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for that which the diuel or thine owne fleſh ſhall ſuggeſt to mooue thee to deſpaire of Gods mercie, that GOD in iuſtice cannot receiue ſuch a rebell wretch as thou haſt bin,
<pb facs="tcp:21561:74"/> aggrauating euery of thy leaſt ſinnes, and telling thee it is in vaine to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent: thou maieſt eaſily beat backe that temptation. T'is true, GOD is not ſo mercifull, to vſe iniuſtice, ſo he is not ſo iuſt to bee vnmercifull: He hath ſuffered mighty and maruailous men to erre, that we by their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might haue comfort, and not deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire of grace and pardon. In holy Scripture who is more commended then King <hi>Dauid,</hi> who was both a King &amp; a Prophet, a man after Gods owne heart, and of whoſe ſtocke the Meſſias came? But into how many and grieuous crimes ſell ſo worthy a man? yet hearing <hi>Nathan</hi> pronounce the fearfull threatnings of God, cried out, <hi>I haue ſinned,</hi> and <hi>Nathan</hi> ſaid; But the Lord hath put away thy ſins, thou ſhalt not die. Haſt thou ſinned with <hi>Dauid?</hi> repent with <hi>Dauid,</hi> and thou ſhalt with <hi>Dauid</hi> finde mercy: What ſhould I tell thee of our firſt parents, of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> of <hi>Zacheus,</hi> of <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> of <hi>Peter,</hi> of <hi>Paul,</hi> of the <hi>Theefe</hi> on the croſſe? all which
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21561:74"/> had beene moſt grieuous ſinners vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth; all which are now moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Saints in heauen: For where ſin aboundeth, there grace ſuperaboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth; and therefore let not the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude nor the magnitude of thy ſinnes diſmay thee, ſeeing the mercy of that Lord to whom thou turneſt, is aboue all: though thy ſinnes were as red as ſcarlet, yet hee will make them as white as ſnow; and though they were of purple hue, yet he will make them as white as the pureſt wooll of the fleece. There cannot be a deeper die then ſcarlet, it is a thing vnpoſſible with men to bring a ſcarlet into whit; yet the Lord ſaith, if we will but talk and come to any reaſon with him, he will make our ſinnes though neuer ſo deep ingraind in any ſcarlet or blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy colur, to turne white and pure, as innocencie it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Read the booke of <hi>Ionah</hi> thorow, and there you ſhall ſee the propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Gods nature to ſhew mercy, liuely ſet forth: And therefore a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther affirmeth the offence of <hi>Iudas</hi> to
<pb facs="tcp:21561:75"/> be greater in deſpairing of mercy, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in betraying the Sonne of God, and <hi>Caine</hi> to haue ſtirred God to anger, more through deſperation of pardon then by the murder of his brother <hi>Abel:</hi> many which nailed Chriſt to the croſſe, being conuerted, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeuing in him, obtained pardon and are made examples to man, that hee ought in no wiſe to diſtruſt the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his wickednes, ſeing the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Lord of glory is forgiuen to the penitent.</p>
               <p>Turne then vnto him, and a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent pardon is made ready, which ſhall be ſigned the firſt houre of thy repentance. When therefore thou fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt in thy heart a ſorrow for ſin, and a feruent deſire to ſerue God, cheriſh it, and take the opportunity of the firſt motion: Enter preſently into thy chamber, or into ſome other ſecret place, and there falling on thy knees beſeech the Lord, that as he hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen thee a deteſtation of ſinne, and a minde of godlines, ſo it may pleaſe him to perfect the good begun by
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21561:75"/> him: to accept thy will, and pardon thy many wants and weakneſſe, in &amp; for the al-ſufficient merits of Chriſt Ieſus: to giue thee grace that thou maieſt go on mourning continually for thy ſinnes; and yet withall to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioice in his ſweet mercies: to put his feare into thy heart, that thou maieſt neuer more depart from him: and ſo to enkindle thy zeale, that the fire thereof may burne vp and conſume euery day more and more thy carnall deſires and natural corruptions. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue this courſe of praying, both mornings and euenings at the leaſt: but if thou canſt oftner, it is the better: For, pray continually, ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle: meaning thou ſhouldeſt haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies good meditations in thy mind: &amp; when thou goeſt to pray, ſtriue to pray in the ſpirit, framing thy petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons according to the feeling of thine own wants, or Gods mercies towards thee (not that I diſallow of ſet praiers, for I reuerence the godly authors and vſers of them) but becauſe hee that hath the gift of extemporall praying,
<pb facs="tcp:21561:76"/> is not ſo eaſily caried away with vaine diſtractio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which Satan prompts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, (his minde and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding being wholly bent to the matter in hand) as commonly they be that pray in the booke of another mans conceiuing. And if thou feele thy ſelfe ſomewhat duller ſometimes, ſound forth thy voice withall, it will help much to the awaking of thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, as by mine owne experience I haue many times found. But take heed as neere as thou canſt, that thy praiers bee out of the hearing of others, leſt thou get the imputation of hypocriſie, and cauſe thy good to be euill ſpoken of.</p>
               <p>And for the further increaſing of thy knowledge, vſe euery morning after praiers to read a chapter of the old or new Teſtament, and another at night likewiſe before praiers, &amp; thou ſhalt find it by the bleſſing of GOD in ſhort time to haue cleared thine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding very much, and diſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the miſtes of thy former igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. Alſo let me wiſh thee to read
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21561:76"/> ſometimes carefully and aduiſedly the 28 chapter of <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> and the 26 of <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> becauſe they bee parts of Scripture, which (if we marke them well) will help much to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vs in the doing of our duties. When thou art tempted to any ſinne, carry not in the place, but goe doe ſomething elſe, till the temptation be ſlackt. Vndertake no waighty buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of thine owne or thy maſters, but with praier before, that God would guide and &amp; ſpeed thee in it. Thinke not that thy praying will loſe thee thy opportunity: <hi>For time is neuer loſt in praying vnto him that doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whatſoeuer hath beene vnto thee an occaſion of ſinne, ſhun it as thou wouldeſt ſhun a moſt mortal danger. Thinke no place to be without a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy doings: for a great part of wickedneſſe is left vndone, if ſome body be by when one is about to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it. Frequent the company of the godly, and auoid the conuerſation of the wicked and prophane: for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall
<pb facs="tcp:21561:77"/> conuerſation is of great force, not only to make vs embrace the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, but oftentimes alſo, euen againſt our willes to imitate the vices of our companions. Hence it commeth, that we are alwayes taken for ſuch as thoſe are, with whom wee doe ordinarily conuerſe, according to the prouerb,
<q>
                     <l>His nature in his mate is ſhowen,</l>
                     <l>Who cannot by himſelfe be knowen.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Meditate often of death, of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of this life, of the reſurrection, the iudgement, and the ioyes of the life to come: rather ſuffer euill then doe euill to any; but neither ſpeake euill, nor liſten to euill ſpeakers. Fall not eaſily at ods with any, but conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue at ods with none. Follow thy God and Sauiours example, in doing well vnto all men, and endeuour to be like him in louing thine enemies. Finally, whatſoeuer things bee of good report, or honeſt example, thoſe things thinke on and doe, and the God of peace ſhall be with thee for euer.</p>
               <p>Theſe things howſoeuer they ſeeme
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21561:77"/> vnpleaſant, and abhorring from our nature, eſpecially in our yong yeares; yet if the Lord once infuſe his grace into our hearts, and renue our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by the working of his ſpirit, they will ſeeme ſweet and eaſie, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull; and we ſhal take more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in doing of them, then in any worldly or bodily exerciſe whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer. All the matter is at firſt, after a little vſe, all difficulty vaniſheth. At the firſt leaping into the water, mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle high, one feeles intollerable cold, ready to take away the breath, but by that time he hath waded in further vp to the necke, it ſeemes to be of a milder temper. So religion and Gods ſeruice ſeemes harſh and tedious at the firſt entry into it, but by that time we haue beene a while inured to the practiſe of it, all other things are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauorie to vs, and onely in this there is heauenly delectation. To conclude this chapter; remember that our fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the want of grace, is a good ſtep to the obtaining of grace: Our deſire to repent, is the ſeed or kernell
<pb facs="tcp:21561:78"/> of repentance; and being cheriſhed, will at length beare ripe fruites of a ſanctified conuerſation. That, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the diuell and our owne fleſh mooue vs to doubting, yet God wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not the death of a ſinner, that doth from the bottome of his heart turne vnto him: nor ſhall our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance be in vaine (ſo it be true) though our ſinnes were as many (for num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) as the drops of raine, and as blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die (for their quality) as skarlet is red. Gods mercy is a rich mercy, and his pardon is abſolute, without limitation or exception. Finally, that hearty and continuall prayer, and ſuch ſimple rules &amp; directions as I haue ſet down out of mine owne obſeruation &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, will prooue good helpes to the new Proſelytes, for the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and perfiting of their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:21561:78"/>
               <head>CHAP. 9.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F any aske how hee ſhall know whether his repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance be true or no; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, by the change which eft-ſoones hee ſhall feele wrought in his whole man; which is in a word the forſaking his former ſinnes wherein he delighted, and delighting in thoſe good things which before hee deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Without this change there is no repentance. Well we may flatter our ſelues, and talke of repentance; but we are yet in our ſins, and the Lords decree is ſtill in force againſt vs. Well then, wilt thou be, not almoſt a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian as <hi>King Agrippa,</hi> but a true Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite indeede, like <hi>Nathaniel</hi> in whom was no guile? renounce all thy olde ſinnes, and receiue in their places the vertues oppoſite to them, and this
<pb facs="tcp:21561:79"/> ſhall ſeale vp to thy conſcience that thy ſinnes are forgiuen for his names ſake.</p>
               <p>Haſt thou beene a ſwearer? from henceforth feare the glorious and fearefull name of the Lord, &amp; thinke not of it but with ſingular reuerence; becauſe his owne mouth hath ſaid it, <hi>He wil not hold him guiltleſſe that taketh his name in vaine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſwere me not, as one did not long ſince being reproued for this ſinne, I am no ſuch great ſwearer, as you would make me; It is but ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that I ſweare by GOD, and by ſuch &amp; ſuch great othes: for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the greateſt othes that I ſweare is but by my faith or troth, and that I make account to be no ſuch great matter, and I pray GOD you neuer do worſe, and then you ſhall do well enough.</p>
               <p>But make thou conſcience of an oth aſwell little as great: for the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle alloweth of no oth at al; Swear not all (ſaith he) neither by heauen nor by earth, nor any oth, leſt you
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21561:79"/> fall into condemnation. But (as our Sauiour ſaith) let your yea be yea, &amp; your nay nay; for whatſoeuer is more is of the Diuell</p>
               <p>O but ſaith one, the world is ſo full of vnbeleefe, that except I ſweare, men will not beleeue me, yea &amp; nay is nothing now a daies to ſell my commodities by, if I ſweare not I ſhal not ſell.</p>
               <p>Why is that, but becauſe thou haſt neuer made conſcience of a lie, but added an oth, two or three ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to make a lie goe currant? and peraduenture thy cuſtomers ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times knowing that thou ſweareſt falſly, cannot beleeue thee another time though thou ſweare truely. But if thou wouldeſt ſell thy wares, take the counſell of the Apoſtle, who willeth vs to caſt off lying, and euery one of vs to ſpeake truth to his neigbour, foraſmuch as we are mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers one of another: and ſo by vſing thy tongue to ſpeake truth, thou ſhalt be beleeued ſooner vpon thy bare word, then vpon thy many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations
<pb facs="tcp:21561:80"/> and othes. Carnall men wil ſooner ſuſpect thy ſwearing, then thy plaine ſaying, becauſe they (though they be ſuch as cary a forme of ciuil honeſty) wil notwithſtanding not ſtick to ſweare a lie themſelues to win ſome aduantage by, and by their own faſhion they iudge of thine. So then ſwearing is a ſin clothed neither with pleaſure nor profit: for what pleaſure is there in a prophane fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy word, ſpewed out of the wicked abundance of the heart? or what profit, when the thundring out of ſix or ſeuen othes one after another will not ſell a yeard of ſtuffe or a pound waight of thy commodities? ſo little account is made of them. Beſides, in much ſwearing is oft forſwearing, as it is ſeen too often in our ſhops eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day: For let a man come into ſome ſhops to cheapen a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity &amp; they will ſweare that they cannot afford it at ſuch a price, and that they will keep it ſeuen yeares before they will ſell it ſo, and yet let their cuſtomers back be no ſooner turned to be gone,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21561:80"/> but preſently he is called againe, and his money taken, which before was refuſed with ſo many othes.</p>
               <p>If Seruants will thus burden their conſciences for their maſters profit, (&amp; many againſt their maſters wils) what will they do for themſelues? who ſhall let them then to ſweare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all faith, truth and conſcience for euer? to ſweare their ſoules to the Diuel, that they ſhall neuer repent; and to ſweare a plague into their houſes, which ſhall conſume the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry timber and ſtones of it? O my Brethren tremble at this prouoking ſinne: tremble to bring the great and holy name of the Lord for a witneſſe to your baſe twelue penny lies: tremble to deale ſo ſaucily with the omnipotent Maieſtie that can ſend a deadly thunderbolt to ſtrike you preſently thorow, in the place where you ſtand. Beare with a vehement ſpeech, when it proceedes out of a loue more vehement: For your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſoules ſake, leaue off this profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and pleaſureleſſe ſinne: let this
<pb facs="tcp:21561:81"/> be the firſt ſinne thou fighteſt againſt, and when thou haſt got the victory of this, the reſt of thy conqueſt will be the eaſier.</p>
               <p>Haſt thou beene a prophaner of the Sabbath, and one that hath made no conſcience of going to Church longer then thy maſters eie hath been vpon thee; and when thou haſt beene there, haſt made ſmall account of that which hath beene taught, but either haſt been talking, or ſleeping, or idly, or wickedly thinking? &amp;c. Henceforth frequent more duely the the holy ſanctuary and houſe of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; prepare thy ſelfe aforehand that thou maieſt reap profit of the things which thou ſhalt heare; intend more reuerently and deuoutly to Gods worſhip: rob not the Lord of the day which he hath conſecrated to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his great name: he requireth but the ſeuenth, ſix are ours, and ſhal we not afford him one?</p>
               <p>If a Father hauing called his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren together ſhould tell them: It is ſo, that I haue caſt vp my accounts,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21561:81"/> and I find my eſtate to be worth ſeuen thouſand pound, ſix of which ſeuen thouſand I am content preſently to part with among you, and the one thouſand ſee you vſe as thriftily and carefully to my behoof, as you would the ſix thouſand to your owne. What ingratitude &amp; vnreuerence were it to ſo bountifull a Father, for theſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren hauing gotten the ſeuen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pound into their hands, to turne all to their owne vſe and aduantage, neuer reſpecting their kinde Fathers good, nor his charge vnto them, or at the moſt ſo careleſly, that it may appeare there is but little religion of their vow in them? The Lord who is our heauenly Father hath giuen vs ſix daies to do our buſineſſe and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires in, and onely one day he hath reſerued to himſelfe, appointing vs to beſtow it in his worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, becauſe that day is his delight, (as the Prophet ſaith:) what negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, what impiety, what contempt can be greater, then for vs to ſpend the whole weeke in following our
<pb facs="tcp:21561:82"/> pleaſures or our drudgeries, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy Sabbath comes, to intrude into our heauenly fathers right, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume that alſo in the carnall workes, or couetous proiects, or ordinary exerciſes of the weeke before; what intolerable auarice is it, or ſacriledge rather, hauing ſo bountiful allowance from our heauenly father, not to be content, vnleſſe we may ſeaze his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar reſeruation into our hands alſo? This is right to haue thouſands of ſheepe paſturing vpon our owne downes, and yet to kill the poore mans onely Lambe, that ſlept in his boſome, for the prouiſion of our houſe.</p>
               <p>But here ſome will ſay, it is true, we muſt lay away all worke on the Sabbath day, but yet to ſell and take money for wares in the ſhop before and after ſeruice, is no great worke, and therfore as good do that as ſtand idle.</p>
               <p>No, I deny it: for as the prouerbe goeth amongſt vs, Thou hadſt better be idle, then ill occupied; ſo they
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21561:82"/> were better ſtand ſtill then vent their commodities: they be both ſins, but ſelling of ware is the greater, how little ſoeuer: for a man may aſwell take 40. pounds that day as one pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny: For Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is broken in both. In the 16 of Exodus GOD condemneth the Iſraelits for purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to gather Manna on the Sabbath day: what eaſier worke could there be then this? nay moreouer it was to be done between fiue and ſix a clock in the morning, when they might haue ſerued GOD all the day after: and they needed not to haue gone far for it neither, but onely come forth of their doores and ſtoop to take it vp. But (marke) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they came forth they found nothing.</p>
               <p>Here is a good leſſon for vs to learne, that as they went out to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Manna on the Sabbath day, and found nothing: ſo the gaines that is gotten by ſelling wares on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day is, iuſt nothing, howſoeuer men are blinded and thinke the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary, for GODS curſe eates it vp,
<pb facs="tcp:21561:83"/> and more too.</p>
               <p>I grant we are not tied to ſo ſtrict an obſeruation of the Sabbath in euery reſpect as the Iewes were: yet thus farre the morall part of the precept doth oblige vs to the worlds end, namely, to do no workes on that day, but workes of holines, or of meere neceſſity: but men now a daies make no bones to ſtep ouer any of Gods lawes, when they bee in the way of their profit: and yet they will be good Chriſtians too.</p>
               <p>We remember that day to pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per our belies with good cheere and fine clothes, and to take our pleaſure, we remember to keep a right Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures Sabbath: but to heare Gods word taught, to lay our petitions in common together in our Churches, and to cal our families together when wee come home, that wee may bee the better for that wee haue heard, which is the right chriſtians Sabbath; this we remember, vtterly to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get.</p>
               <p>I am perſwaded there is more wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21561:83"/> committed both by Pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes and others on the Lords day, then on any three daies in the weeke beſide, and the reaſon is, becauſe men for the moſt part will ſee that their ſeruants ſhall follow the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their trades all the weeke, but vpon Gods day they are careles of them, and ſuffer them to do what they liſt themſelues. That is the day of their recreation: For as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith, it is a paſtime to a foole to doe euill.</p>
               <p>When they ſhould walke to the Lecture, for the recreation of their ſoules, the maſters are walkt to their gardens or the fields for their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily pleaſure; and the ſeruants to the Tauerne or to ſome place of greater corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the enda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gering of their ſoules: ſo the word preached to them in the day time before, is no better then the ſeed that fell vpon ſtony ground, becauſe for want of due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſal afterward (which is as it were the depth of earth) it withereth away and comes to nothing, like ſeed caſt
<pb facs="tcp:21561:84"/> away vpon the rock where it cannot take root.</p>
               <p>And in this point the irreligiouſnes of Prentiſes doth farre exceed the negligence of maſters: For it is too apparant that many ſeruants would ſeldome or neuer come to Church at all, if it were not more for diſpleaſing their maſters on earth, then for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing their maſter in heauen: For let maſters vpon occaſion bee from home a moneth or two, and all that time if his ſeruants come to Church in the forenoone onely, they thinke they are meetly well in the faſhion: but commonly you ſhal not ſee them there either forenoone or afternoone: and their reaſon is, their maſters ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is the time of their liberty, and they may not ſuffer ſuch good daies to ſlip away without fruit. If you aske them how they wil anſwere it to their maſters at their comming home? they will tell you, they hope their maſters knowledge goeth but by his eie. If you aske the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> how they will anſwer it to GOD, that ſeeth and iudgeth
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21561:84"/> the moſt ſecret workes? they make a piſh at that, or giue you ſome groſſe flout for recompence. But let ſuch know that pouertie and ſhame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs vnto them for refuſing inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and they that thinke now the Lords day, (though it were a moneth long to flie away as one minut in their pleaſures, ſhall hereafter thinke one minute too lag, and paſſe by as ſlowly as a whole yeare in their paines.</p>
               <p>But here ſome may reply, Will you not allow vs to recreate our ſelues at any time? If you ſay yes: then I pray what day haue we that be prentiſes to take our recreation in but the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day? For all the weeke wee are kept ſo ſtraight that we cannot ſo much as get out to ſpeake with any friend. And as for keeping our Church due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, howſoeuer others be negligent, yet it is well knowne in our pariſh that we neuer almoſt miſſe one Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day in the yeare, but wee are alwaies at Church with the firſt, and neuer go into the fields or to any merrime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:21561:85"/> vntil euening praier be done, and then I hope the matter is not ſo hainous as you make it.</p>
               <p>Surely if you were ſuch diligent goers to Church, as you ſay you are, it could not be but you ſhould heare at ſometime or other that you ought not to prophane or miſpend one houre of the Sabbath, where you make it lawfull to ſpend halfe the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoone in merriment and pleaſure. But it may be you are aſleepe when you ſhould heare that; or elſe you take it to be but the word of a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall man, and the authority thereof to vaniſh with the ſpeaking. But a day will come when you ſhall know it was the eternall truth of the GOD of heauen, which his miniſters deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered; and when it will cut your heart to remember that you did heare ſuch a Preacher in ſuch a yeare, in ſuch a moneth, in ſuch a day<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in ſuch a Church, denounce the fearefull iudgements of God againſt ſuch a ſin which you did vſe, and wherein (for a little pleaſures ſake) you did obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21561:85"/> continue to your owne damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>To conclude, haſt thou beene a drunkard? now learne ſobriety: haſt thou been intemperate? now embrace chaſtity: haſt thou beene malicious? ſhew charity: proud? be humble. Finally, whatſoeuer vice thou haſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted thy ſelfe to, recline now to the contrary ſide. That which thou doeſt, do it with all thy power in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time, euen in this day of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For time being once paſt, can neuer be recalled; and to truſt vpon time to come is as much as if we ſhold truſt vpon a broken ſtaffe, the ſplin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters whereof will run into our hand; or ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture to paſſe ſo dangerous a gulſe as damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with a tottering planck (delay I meane) which hath tilted ſo many thouſands into hell before vs.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:21561:86"/>
            <head>THE FOVRTH PART.</head>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 10.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>AVING ſhewed the ineſtimable loue and mercy of GOD to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant ſinners, that do truely forſake their former wickedneſſe, I thinke it neceſſary in the laſt place (as the Lord will enable mee) to ſhew the good &amp; profit of afflictions to Gods children, to the end they may not bee diſcomforted or ſhrinke backe at the ſight of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 2.1.</note>My ſonne, (ſaith the Sonne of <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach</hi>) if thou come into the ſeruice of GOD, ſtand faſt in righteouſnes and feare, and prepare thy ſoule to tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21561:86"/> and ſhrinke not when thou art troubled, but wait patiently vpon God. And it is a ſealed truth which the Apoſtle hath deliuered, All that will liue godly in Chriſt Ieſus ſhall ſuffer perſecution, in one kind or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, more or leſſe. It is their portion and euer hath beene; Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe the author of our faith was not exempted, and the ſeruant is not aboue his Lord.</p>
               <p>If then afflictions muſt needes bee vndergone, let vs labour to vndergo them willingly, which muſt bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone of neceſſity. I know there is a certaine tendernes in our nature, which with reproches and ill turnes is ſo preſſed and wrung, that there is ſcarſe any man to be found ſo wiſe or couragious, but when he feeles the prickes and ſtings thereof pearcing him, is oftentimes halfe in the minde to giue ouer his courſe of godlineſſe, and turne from the way of vertue. No affliction or vexation for the preſent ſeemeth ioious, but grieuous, ſaith the Apoſtle, but afterward it bringeth
<pb facs="tcp:21561:87"/> forth the quiet fruits of righteouſnes to them that are exerciſed therby. Let vs not dwell then vpon the preſent feeling, but looke further into the ſweet effects and end of our troubles, &amp; thence gather comfort &amp; ſtrength againſt them.</p>
               <p>This made the Apoſtle breake out, <hi>My Brethren,</hi> count it for an excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ioy, when yee fall into diuers tentations; becauſe they are pledges of Gods loue, trials of our faith, and breeders of patience, experience and hope, which neuer makes aſhamed. Art thou entred into a courſe of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and ſanctification? art thou iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for the Lord of Hoſtes? and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thou meet with oppoſitions and ſtumbling blockes in thy way? be not diſmaied, was it not told thee before, the way to heauen lay by the croſſe? It is a ſure ſigne thou art in the path that leades thither. Art thou skoffed at by worldlings &amp; prophan people,<note place="margin">Iob. 21.14.</note> men or women? (for I know diuers ſuch perſons of both ſexes, that being not content to liue in igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:21561:87"/> themſelues, without any deſire to know the way of the Lord, do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride and point at thoſe that ſeeke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction?) Let the clearnes of thy conſcience, and thy holy deſire and endeuour to the beſt things, be as a braſen wall, and a ſtrong tower a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe euils: let them know that the Lord hateth thoſe that ſit in the ſeat of the ſcorneful:<note place="margin">Pſalm. 1.</note> and though they pleaſe themſelues well enough the while, yet it ſhall not be well with them at the laſt day:<note place="margin">Eſay. 3.10</note> For the reward of their owne hands ſhall be giuen them.</p>
               <p>Haſt thou a maſter that entreates thee hardly for thy well doing and thy righteous profeſſions ſake? know that the Lord hath ſet ſuch a maſter ouer thee for thine euerlaſting good, to try thy conſtancy, or to make thee more feruent in thy prayers, or to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh thy loue of the world, or for an example of patience, or an inſtance of comfort to others in like caſe. As many as I loue, I rebuke and chaſten, ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt.<note place="margin">Apoc. 3.19.</note> Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:21561:88"/> be the inſtrument, the chaſtening is Chriſts; ſee that thou do thy duty vnto thy maſter, to the vttermoſt of thy power though he be neuer ſo moody, euen as if he were another <hi>Moſes,</hi> the mildeſt man vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth; that the name of God &amp; his doctrine be not euill ſpoken of. Aſſure thy ſelfe he ſhal be no harder to thee then the Lord ſhall ſee good and expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for thee: for we ſee ſome men want neither power nor will, who ſomtimes in their ſudde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anger would kil their ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts; but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſts his prouidence towards his children, in reſtraining them from thoſe outrages, which in that madding paſſion, they are incited to. Pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, to turne thy maſters heart, that hee may haue a feeling of his ſinnes, that ſo he may come to repentance; and in the meane time, ouercome thou his euill with good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and the Lord will either vnex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectedly alter his wil and affections, or allow thee ſuch other ſecret ioyes as ſhall ouerballance all thy griefes
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:21561:88"/> and diſcomforts.</p>
               <p>If then thou wilt goe to heauen thou ſeeſt the iorney thither lies not in plaine waies; thou muſt goe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row good report and bad, deriſions and skornes, and moleſtations: but the end of the iorney is a ſufficient recompence for all cumbers and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences of the way; the paines are light and momentany, the waight of glory to which they bring vs, is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable and euerlaſting.</p>
               <p>So long as thou waſt of the world, the world loued her owne; now that thou haſt forſaken and bid defiance to her, ſhe takes thee for an enemy, &amp; loades thee with hatred, diſdaine, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy, ſlander and all maner of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. No matter, all this (&amp; worſe) ſhall worke to the beſt to them that loue God, when the ſoftnes and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy and eaſe of worldlings, ſhall be their owne deſtruction.</p>
               <p>All the holy men of old time, all the cheefe lights of the Church, all thoſe that now walke in long white robes with palmes of victory in their
<pb facs="tcp:21561:89"/> hands, yea he that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw in the middeſt of the ſeuen golden can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſtickes, whoſe face did ſhine as the Sunne in his ſtrength, euen he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hath begunne to vs in this bitter cup; and ſhall we ſhrinke to pledge them, when there are but a few ſmal drops left for vs to ſip off?</p>
               <p>If carnall men ſuffer ſo much to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie their luſts, to get riches or dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, to feed themſelues with a little ſmoake of vaine glory, or to taſte ſome ſleight pleaſure which bringes repentance at her heeles. If they feare not the waues of the ſea, nor the flames of fire, nor the croſſings of men, to attaine theſe; ſhall we be ſo without all heart, or ſo nice that wee will not abide a ſcoffe, or a reproch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full word, to attaine thoſe ſolid, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall and eternall pleaſures and good things; in compariſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of which, all the honours, riches, commodities, allurements &amp; ſweetnes of the world, are to bee eſteemed not onely toyes and trifles, but very dregs and droſſe &amp; refuſe, not worth the taking vp?
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21561:89"/> No, no, when we haue once reſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vowed our ſelues to Gods ſeruice, GOD putteth another ſpirit into vs, and a generous heart, (that though we be ſometimes moued with theſe oppoſitions) yet wee are neuer ſo farre oppreſſed by them as to forſake our righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or caſt our lot in amongſt ſinners; but in the middeſt of them our eie is ſo fixt vpon the end of our race, and the heauenly gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land reſerued for ſuch as perſeuere and hold on, that ſhrewd words ſerue as a good gale of wind, and ſhrewd deedes as a violent ſtreame to carry vs the more ſwift towards the port where wee would be.</p>
               <p>Thus hauing finiſhed this ſmall Treatiſe, I would beſeech you (as the Apoſtle ſaith) to ſuffer theſe few lines of exhortations,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.</note> and that you faint not in your afflictions; but bee ſtrong in the Lord, putting on the whole armour of GOD, that yee may be able to ſtand againſt all
<pb facs="tcp:21561:90"/> the aſſaults of the Diuell, hauing your loynes girt about with veritie, and hauing on the breaſt plate of righteouſneſſe, and your feet ſhod with the preparation of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of peace; and aboue all take the ſhield of faith, wherewith yee may quench all the firy darts of the wicked, and take the helmet of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and the ſword of the ſpirit which is the word of GOD, that being thus armed with theſe ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all weapons, ye may bee able to wreſtle againſt principalities and powers, and againſt our ſpirituall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies the gouernors of the darknes of this world.</p>
               <p>Now the Lord from heauen raine downe his grace into our hearts, and ſtrengthen vs with might in the inner man, that wee may ſtand faſt, and encourage one another againſt all the bents of worldly aduerſitie, that being rooted and grounded in loue, we may be able to comprehend with all Saints what is the bredth and length, depth, and height,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:21561:90"/> and know the loue of Chriſt, which paſſeth all knowledge, that wee may bee filled with all ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God. Vnto him therfore (that is able to do exceeding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantlie, aboue all that we can aske or thinke) be all praiſe, glory, maieſty, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and power, thorowout all ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations both now and for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:21561:91"/>
            <head>A Morning Praier to be vſed <hi>in priuate families.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> LORD, our God, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, we thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy children do heere come into thy moſt holy &amp; heauenly preſence, to giue thee praiſe and glory, for all thy great mercies and manifold bleſſings to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs: eſpecially for that thou haſt preſerued vs this night paſt from all the dangers and feares therof, haſt giuen vs quiet reſt to our bodies, &amp; brought vs now ſafely to the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this day, and doeſt now a freſh renue all thy mercies vpon vs, as the Eagle renueth her bill, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs all things abundantly to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy; as food, raiment, health, peace, liberty, &amp; freedome from many mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, diſeaſes, caſualties, &amp; calamities
<pb facs="tcp:21561:91"/> which we are ſubiect vnto in this life, euery minute of an houre: and not onely ſo, but alſo for vouchſafing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs many good things, not onely for neceſſity, but euen for delight alſo. But aboue all (deare Father) we praiſe thy name for the bleſſings of a better life, ſpecially for thy moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly word and ſacraments, and all the good we enioy thereby; for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the Goſpell amongſt vs; for the death of thy Sonne &amp; all that happineſſe which we haue thereby; alſo becauſe thou haſt choſen vs to life before we were, and that of thy meere godnes, and vndeſerued ſauour towards vs, and haſt called vs in thine appointed time, iuſtified vs by thy grace, ſanctified vs by thy Spirit, &amp; adopted vs to be thine own children, &amp; heirs apparent to the great crown. O Lord ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our eies euery day more &amp; more, to ſee &amp; conſider of thy great and maruellous loue to vs in all theſe things; that by the due conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therof, our hearts may be drawen yet neerer vnto thee, euen more to
<pb facs="tcp:21561:92"/> loue thee, feare thee, and obey thee: that as thou art enlarged towards vs in mercy, ſo we may be enlarged to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee in thankeſgiuing: and as thou doeſt abound towards vs in goodnes ſo we may abound towards thee in obedience and loue. And ſith (deere Father) thou art neuer weary of doing vs good, notwithſtanding al our vnworthines and naughtineſſe: therefore let the conſideration of thy great mercy and fatherly kindneſſe towards vs euen as it were force our hearts, and compell vs to come into thy moſt glorious preſence with new ſongs of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keſgiuing in our mouths. We pray thee (O moſt merciful God) to forgiue vs all our vnthankefulnes, vnkindneſſe, prophaneneſſe, &amp; great abuſing of thy mercies, and ſpecially our abuſe and contempt of thy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, together with all other the ſinnes of our life, which we confeſſe are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable, and moe than can be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned vp, both in omiſſion of good things and commiſſion of euill. We moſt humbly intreat thee to ſet them
<pb facs="tcp:21561:92"/> all ouer to the reckoning which thy ſon Chriſt hath made vp for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon his croſſe, and neuer to lay any of them to our charge, but freely for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get all, and forgiue all; Naile downe all our ſinnes and iniquities to the Croſſe of Chriſt, bury them in his death, bathe them in his bloud, hide them in his wounds, let them neuer riſe vp in iudgement againſt vs. Set vs free of the miſeries that are vpon vs for ſin, and keep backe the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to come, both of ſoule, body, goods, and good name. Be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto vs in thy deere Sonne, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning all matters paſt, not once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring or repeating vnto vs our old and abominable iniquities; but accept vs as righteous in him, impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his righteouſneſſe to vs, and our ſinnes to him. Let his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſatisfie thy iuſtice for all our vnrighteouſneſſe, his obedience for our diſobedience, his perfection for our imperfection. Moreouer, we humbly beſeech thy good maieſty to giue vs the true ſight and feeling of
<pb facs="tcp:21561:93"/> our manifold ſinnes, that we may not be blinded in them through delight, or hardened in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through cuſtome as the reprobates are: but that wee may be euen weary of them, and much grieued for them labouring and ſtriuing by all poſſible meanes to get out of them. Good Father touch our hearts with true repentance for all ſinne. Let vs not take any delight or pleaſure in any ſinne: but howſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer we fall through frailty (as wee fall often) yet let vs neuer fall finally, let vs neuer lie downe in ſinne, nor continue in ſinne; but let vs get vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our feet againe, and turne to thee with all our hearts, and ſeeke thee whileſt thou maieſt be found, and whileſt thou doſt offer grace &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vnto vs. O Lord increaſe in vs that true and liuely faith whereby we may lay ſure hold on thy Sonne Chriſt, and reſt vpon his merits al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together. Giue vs faith aſſuredly to beleeue all the great and precious promiſes made in the Goſpell, and ſtrengthen vs from aboue to walke
<pb facs="tcp:21561:93"/> and abound in all true &amp; ſound fruits of faith. Let vs walke not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit. Let vs feele the power of thy Sons death killing ſinne in our mortall bodies, and the power of his reſurrection, raiſing vs vp to newneſſe of life. Let vs grow daily in the ſanctification of the ſpirit, and the mortification of the fleſh. Let vs liue holily, iuſtly, and ſoberly in this preſent euill world, ſhewing forth the vertues of thee in al our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular actions; that we may adorne our moſt holy profeſſion, and ſhine as lights in the middeſt of a crooked and froward generation amongſt whom we liue, being gainfull to all by our liues and conuerſations, and offenſiue to none. To this end wee pray thee fill vs with thy ſpirit and al ſpiritual graces; as loue, wiſedome, patience, contentment, meekeneſſe, humility, temperancy, chaſtity, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and affability: and ſtirre vs vp to vſe praier and watchfulneſſe, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and meditation in thy law, and all other good meanes whereby wee
<pb facs="tcp:21561:94"/> may grow and abound in all heauenly vertues. Bleſſe vs in the vſe of the meanes, from day to day; make vs ſuch as thou wouldeſt haue vs to bee, and ſuch as we deſire to be, working in vs both will and deed, purpoſe and power. For thou O Lord art all in all, thou wilt haue mercy vpon whom thou wilt haue mercy, &amp; who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou wilt thou hardeneſt. Haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vpon vs therefore (deere Father) and neuer leaue vs to our ſelues, nor to our owne wils, luſts, and deſires, but aſſiſt vs with thy good ſpirit, that we may continue to the end in a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous courſe; that ſo at length we may be receiued into glory, and be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of that immortal crown which thou haſt laid vp for all that loue thee and truely call vpon thee.</p>
            <p>Further, we entreat thee, O hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father, to giue vs all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for this life: as food, raiment, health, peace, liberty, and ſuch free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from thoſe manifold miſeries which we lie open vnto euery day, as thou ſeeſt meet. Bleſſe vnto vs all the
<pb facs="tcp:21561:94"/> meanes which thou haſt put into our hands, for the ſuſtenance of this fraile life. Bleſſe our ſtocke &amp; ſtore, corne, and cattell, trades and occupations, and all the workes of our hands: for thy bleſſing onely maketh rich, and it bringeth no ſorrowes with it. Giue vs therefore ſuch a competency and ſufficiency of theſe outward bleſſings as thou in thy heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly wiſdome ſeeſt moſt needfull for vs. Moreouer, we humbly beſeech thee, (moſt louing Father) in great mercy to looke downe from heauen vpon thy whole Church, and euery member of it. Be fauourable vnto <hi>Sten,</hi> and build vp the wals of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> Behold with the eie of pity, the great ruines and deſolations of thy Church. Heale vp the wounds, and make vp the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches thereof in all Nations. Regard it as thine owne flocke, tender it as thine owne family, dreſſe it as thine owne vinyeard loue it as thine owne ſpouſe. Thinke thoughts of peace to it, and alwaies looke vpon it in deep compaſſion. Bleſſe it with thy grace,
<pb facs="tcp:21561:95"/> guide it with thy ſpirit, and defend it alwaies with thy mightie power: ſcatter the deuices, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>found the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, &amp; ouerthrow the forces of all that fight againſt it. Specially we intreat thee, deere father, to ſet thy ſelf againſt that Antichriſt of Rome, that man of perdition which ſetteth himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, and againſt all thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. In thine appointed time we pray thee giue him a deadly downe fal. Beat downe all his power and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity daily more and more: giue free paſſage to thy Goſpell in all king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, that <hi>Babylon</hi> may fall and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer riſe vp againe. The more the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourites &amp; adherents of <hi>Rome</hi> labour to vphold their idolatrous king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the more let it fall downe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as <hi>Dagon</hi> before the preſence of thine Ark. Powre downe the vials of the fulneſſe of thy wrath vpon the kingdome of the Beaſt, and let their riches, wealth, credit and authority, drie vp euery day more and more, as the riuer <hi>Euphrates.</hi> Let it pity thee, O Father, to ſee thine owne ſpouſe ſit
<pb facs="tcp:21561:95"/> as a deformed and forlorne woman heere below weeping and mourning with haire about her necke, hauing loſt all her beauty and comlineſſe: cheere her vp (deere Father) glad her with the ioy of thy countenance, and ſo decke her and trimme her vp that thou maieſt delight in her, as a Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome in his Bride. Specially we in treat thee to haue mercy vpon th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Church in this land: intend good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs and not euill: giue vs not ouer into the hands of the cruell <hi>Spaniard,</hi> as our ſinnes haue deſerued. Scatter we pray thee, O Lord, the deuices &amp; breake the plots of all ſuch as haue plotted the ouerthrow and vtter ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſion of this Church and common wealth. Bleſſe this Church more &amp; more, with the continuance of true Religion amongſt vs. For thy great names ſake and infinite mercies ſake deale gratiouſly and fauourably with vs and our poſterity. Turne from vs that vengeance which is due to vs for our ſinnes. For thou ſeeſt how ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity preuaileth and the wicked goe
<pb facs="tcp:21561:96"/> away with the goale. Atheiſme ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpreadeth euery where, and Poperie ſeemeth to get a head againe. Now therefore (deere Father) wee moſt humbly beſeech thee to take order ſpeedily for the remedying and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of theſe manifold diſorders, and grieuous enormities that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs. Be intreated of thy poore children to be good to this Engliſh nation. Heare the cries of thine elect: heare the mourning of them that mourne in Sion. Let the cries of thy children crie downe all the cries of the ſinnes of the land, and be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto vs in the multitude of thy compaſſions: that ſo thou maieſt ſtill continue a moſt mercifull protector of this thine Engliſh vineyard. Wee pray thee (good Father) ſhew ſpecial mercy to our moſt Noble and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous K. <hi>Iames</hi> thine anointed ſeruant: bleſſe him, and keep him in all his waies. Bleſſe his gouernment vnto vs. Let thine Angels encamp about him, and let thy holy hand be alwaies o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him, keep him from treaſons, and
<pb facs="tcp:21561:96"/> deliuer him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the treacheries of his enemies: giue him to ſee what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth vnto his peace, and giue him a heart earneſtly bent to ſet vpon the practiſe of the ſame: giue him al gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces neceſſary for his peace, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for his ſaluation: continue his gouernement peaceable and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous amongſt vs: and as thou haſt made him the breath of our noſtrils, and a gratious inſtrument for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of many thouſand ſoules, ſo let his owne ſoule be ſaued in the day of thy Sonne Chriſt. Bleſſe his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties moſt honorable priuy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, and giue ſuch good ſucceſſe vnto all their Counſels and policies in matters of ſtate, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable life in all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and honeſty. Bleſſe all the Nobility, worke in them a care to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie thy name in their places, make them faithfull to thee, and faithful to the Land. Direct with thy good ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit all ſuch as beare the ſword of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, that they may draw it out to puniſh the wicked, and to defend the
<pb facs="tcp:21561:97"/> godly, &amp; that they may with al good care and conſcience diſcharge the duties of their places. Increaſe the number of faithfull &amp; zealous Mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters in this Church. Send thy Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell to thoſe places where it is not, &amp; bleſſe it where it is. Remember them in thy mercy, O Lord, that are vnder any croſſe or affliction what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer: bee comfortable vnto them heale vp their wounds, binde vp their ſores, put all their teares into thy bottle, and make their bed in all their ſorrowes, and put ſuch a good end to al their troubles that they may redound to thy glory, and the furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of their owne ſaluation. In the meane time giue them patience and conſtancy to beare whatſoeuer it ſhal pleaſe thy merciful hand to lay vpon them. Laſt of all, in a word wee pray thee bleſſe Magiſtracie, Miniſtery &amp; Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monalty. Bleſſe all thy people do good to all that are true and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in their hearts. And ſo (deere fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) we do commit &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend our ſelues, our ſoules &amp; bodies, into thy
<pb facs="tcp:21561:97"/> hands, for this day and the reſt of our life, praying thee to take care and charge of vs; keep vs from all euill, watch ouer vs for our good, let thine Angels encamp about vs, let thy holy hand be ouer vs, and keep vs in all our waies, that we may liue to thy praiſe and glory here in earth, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faith and a good conſcience in all our actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; that after this life we may be crowned of thee for euer in thy kingdome. Grant theſe things (good father) to vs here preſent, and to all thine abſent; praying thee in ſpeciall fauour to remember our friends and kinsfolkes in the fleſh, all our good neighbours and wel-willers, and all thoſe for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are bound to pray by nature, by deſerts, or any duty whatſoeuer, for Ieſus Chriſts ſake our onely Mediator; to whom with thee and the holy Ghoſt, be giuen all praiſe and glory, both now and for euermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:21561:98"/>
            <head>An Euening prayer to be vſed <hi>in priuate families.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Eternall GOD, and moſt louing &amp; deare Father, we thy vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy children, do heere fall downe at the foot of thy great maieſty, acknowledging from our hearts, that we are altogether vnworthy to come neere thee or to look towards thee: becauſe thou art a God of infinit glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and we are moſt vile, and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable ſinners, ſuch as were concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and borne in ſinne and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſuch as haue inherited our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers corruptions, and alſo haue actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally tranſgreſſed all thy holy ſtatutes and lawes, both in thought, words, &amp; deeds, before we knew thee: &amp; ſince, ſecretly and openly, with our ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:21561:98"/> and with others, our particular ſinnes are moe than can be numbred: for who knoweth how often hee offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth? But this we muſt needes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe againſt our ſelues, that our hearts are full of pride, couetouſneſſe, and the loue of this world, full of wrath, anger, and impatiencie, full of lying, diſſembling, and deceiuing, full of vanity, hardneſſe, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſſe, full of infidelity, diſtruſt, and ſelfe-loue, full of luſt, vncleane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and all abhominable deſires: yea our hearts are the very ſinkes of ſin, &amp; dunghils of all filthines. And beſides all this, we do omit the good things we ſhould doe: for there are in vs great wants of faith, of loue, of zeale, of patience, of contentment, &amp; of euery good grace; ſo as thou haſt iuſt cauſe to proceed to ſentence of iudgement againſt vs, as moſt dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable tranſgreſſors of all thy holy commandements: yea ſuch as are ſunke in our rebellions, and haue many times &amp; often committed high treaſon againſt thy maieſty, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:21561:99"/> thou maieſt iuſtly caſt vs all downe into hell fire, there to be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with Satan, and his Angels for euer. And wee haue nothing to except againſt thy maieſty for ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: ſith therin thou ſhouldeſt deale with vs but according to equity, and our iuſt deſerts. Wherefore deere father we doe appeale from thy iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to thy mercy, moſt humbly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treating thee to haue mercy vpon vs, and freely to forgiue vs all our ſinnes paſt whatſoeuer, both new and old, ſecret and open, knowen and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen, and that for Ieſus Chriſts ſake, our onely Mediator. And wee pray thee touch our hearts with true griefe, and vnfained repentance for them, that they may be a matter of continuall ſorrow, and heart-ſmart vnto vs, ſo as nothing may greiue vs more then this, that we haue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thee being our ſpeciall friend and father. Giue vs therefore (deere Father) euery day more and more ſight and feeling of our ſinnes, with true humiliation vnder the ſame.
<pb facs="tcp:21561:99"/> Giue vs alſo that true and liuely faith, wherby we may lay ſure hold onthy Son Chriſt, and all his merits, aply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame to our owne ſoules; ſo as we may ſtand fully perſwaded that whatſoeuer hee hath done vpon the croſſe, he hath done for vs particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as well as for others. Giue vs faith (good Father) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly to beleeue al the ſweet promiſes of the goſpel, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching remiſſion of ſinne, and eternall life, made in thy Sonne Chriſt. O Lord increaſe our faith, that we may altogether reſt vpon thy promiſes, which are all, yea, and Amen Yea, that we may ſettle our ſelues, and all that we haue wholly vpon them: both our ſoules, bodies, goods, name, wiues children, &amp; our whole eſtate, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all things depend vpon thy promiſes, power, and prouidence, &amp; that thy word doth ſupport &amp; beare vp the whole order of nature. More ouer, we intreat thee, O Lord, to ſtrengthen vs from aboue to walke in euery good way, and to bring forth the fruits of true faith in all our
<pb facs="tcp:21561:100"/> particular actions, ſtudying to pleaſe thee in all things and to be fruitfull in good workes, that we may ſhew forth vnto all men by our good conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whoſe children wee are: and that we may adorne and beautifie our moſt holy profeſſion by walking in a Chriſtian courſe, and in all the ſound fruits and practiſe of godlines, and true religion. To this end wee pray thee ſanctifie our hearts by thy ſpirit yet more and more: ſanctifie our ſoules and bodies, and all our corrupt naturall faculties, as reaſon, vnderſtanding, will, and affections, ſo as they may be fitted for thy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſeruice, taking a delight and pleaſure therein. Stirre vs vp to vſe praier; watchfulneſſe, reading and meditation in thy law, and all other good meanes whereby we may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit in grace and goodneſſe from day to day. Bleſſe vs in the vſe of the meanes, that we may daily die to ſin, and liue to righteouſneſſe: draw vs yet neerer vnto thee: help vs againſt our monifold wants. Amend our
<pb facs="tcp:21561:100"/> great imperfections, renue vs inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more and more, repaire the ruines of our hearts, aide vs againſt the remnants of ſin. Enlarge our hearts to runne the way of thy Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, direct all our ſteps in thy word, let none iniquity haue domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ouer vs. Aſſiſt vs againſt our ſpecial infirmities, and maſter ſinnes, that wee may get the victory ouer them all, to thy glory, and the great peace and comfort of our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences. Strengthen vs, good father, by thy grace and holy ſpirit, againſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon corruptions of the world, as pride, whoredome, couetouſneſſe, contempt of thy Goſpell, ſwearing, lying, diſſembling, and deceiuing. O deere Father, let vs not be ouer come of theſe filthy vices, nor any other ſinfull pleaſures, and fond delights, wherwith thouſands are caried head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to deſtruction. Arme our ſoules againſt all the temptations of this world, the fleſh and the Diuell: that we may ouercome them all through thy help, and keep on the right way
<pb facs="tcp:21561:101"/> to life, that we may liue in thy feare, and die in thy fauour, that our laſt daies may be our beſt daies, and that we may end in great peace of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Furthermore, deere Father, we intreat thee not onely for ourſelues, but for all our good brethren thy deere children ſcattered ouer the face of the whole earth, moſt humbly beſeeching thee to bleſſe them all, to cheere them vp, and glad them with the ioy of thy countenance both now and alwaies. Guide them all in thy feare, and keep them from euill, that they may praiſe thy name. In theſe dangerous daies, and declining times, we pray thee, O Lord, raiſe vp nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing fathers and nurſing mothers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Church. Raiſe vp alſo faithful Paſtors, that thy cauſe may be caried forward, truth may preuaile, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may proſper, thy name onely may be ſet vp in the earth, thy Sonnes kingdome aduanced, and thy will accompliſhed. Set thy ſelfe againſt all aduerſary power, eſpecially that of Rome, Antichriſt, Idolatry, and
<pb facs="tcp:21561:101"/> Atheiſme: curſe and croſſe all their counſels, fruſtrate their deuiſes, ſcatter their forces, ouerthrow their armies. When they are moſt wiſe, let them be moſt fooliſh: when they are moſt ſtrong, let them be moſt weake. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> know that there is no wiſdom nor cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel, power nor policy againſt thee the Lord of Hoſts. Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> know that <hi>Iſrael</hi> hath a God, &amp; that thou which art called <hi>Iehouah</hi> art the onely ruler ouer all the world. Ariſe therefore O moſt mightie God, and maintaine thine owne cauſe againſt all thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, ſmite thorow all their loines, and bow downe their backes, yea let them all be confounded, and turned backward that beare ill will vnto <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Let the patient abiding of the righteous be ioy: and let the wicked be diſappointed of their hope. But of all fauour, we intreate thee O Lord, to ſhew ſpecial mercy to thy Church in this Land wherein we liue. Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue thy Goſpell amongſt vs yet with greater ſucceſſe, purge thy houſe dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more &amp; more, take away all things
<pb facs="tcp:21561:102"/> that offend. Let this Nation ſtill bee a place where thy name may bee called vpon, and an harbour for thy Saints. Shew mercy to our poſterity, deare Father, and haue care of them, that thy Goſpell may bee left vnto them as a moſt holy inheritance. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend vs againſt forre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, keep out Idolatry and Popery from amongſt vs. Turne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs thoſe plagues which our ſins cry for. For the ſins of this Land are exceeding great, horrible, and outragious, &amp; giue thee iuſt cauſe to make vs ſpectacles of thy venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to all Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; that by how much the more thou haſt lifted vs vp in great mercy, and long peace by ſo much the more thou ſhouldeſt preſſe vs downe in great wrath &amp; long war. Therfore deere Father, we moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly intreat thee, for thy great names ſake, and for thy infinit mercies ſake, that thou wouldeſt bee reconciled to this land, and diſcharge it of all the horrible ſins thereof. Drowne them O Lord in thy infinit mercy through Chriſt, as it were in a bottomeleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:21561:102"/> gulfe, that they may neuer riſe vp in iudgement againſt vs. For although our ſinnes bee exceeding many, and feareful, yet thy mercy is far greater. For thou art infinite in mercy, but we cannot be infinite in ſinning. Giue vs not ouer into the hands of the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, leſt they ſhould blaſpheme thy name, and ſay, Where is their God in whom they truſted? But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, deere father, take vs into thine owne hands, and correct vs accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy wiſedome: for with thee is mercy, &amp; deep compaſſion. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, wee moſt heartily beſeech thy good Maieſty to bleſſe our moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious King <hi>Iames,</hi> and to ſhew much mercy to him in all things. Guide him in thy feare, and keep him in all his waies, working in his ſoule vnfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſorrow for ſinne, true faith in the promiſes, &amp; a great care to pleaſe thee in all things, and to diſcharge the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his high place, in all zeale of thy glory, and faithfulneſſe towards thy Maieſty: that as thou haſt crowned him heere in earth, ſo hee (ſpending
<pb facs="tcp:21561:103"/> his daies, heere below in thy feare) may after this life be crowned of thee for euer in the Heauens. We beſeech thee alſo to bleſſe his Maieſties moſt honorable priuie Counſellors. Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell them from aboue, let them take aduice of thee in all things: that they may both conſult, and reſolue of ſuch courſes as may be moſt for thy glory, the good of the Church, &amp; the peace of this our Commonwealth. Bleſſe the Nobility, and all the Magiſtrates in the Land, giuing them all grace to execute iudgement and iuſtice, and to maintaine truth and equity. Bleſſe all the faithfull Miniſters of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, increaſe the number of them, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>increaſe thy gifts in them: and ſo bleſſe all their labours in their ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall places and congregations, that they all may bee inſtruments of thy hand to inlarge thy Sonnes king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and to winne many vnto thee. Comfort the comfortleſſe with all needfull comforts. Forget none of thine that are in trouble: but as their afflictions are, ſo let the ioyes
<pb facs="tcp:21561:103"/> and comforts of thy ſpirit bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: and ſo ſanctifie vnto all thine, their afflictions and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, that they may tend to thy glory, and their owne good. Giue vs thankefull hearts for all thy mercies, both ſpirituall and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall: for thou art very mercifull vnto vs in the things of this life, and infinitely more mercifull in the things of a better life. Let vs deeply ponder and waigh all thy particular fauoures towards vs: that by the due conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, our hearts may bee gained yet neerer vnto thee, and that therefore wee may both loue and obey thee, becauſe thou art ſo kind and louing vnto vs: that euen thy loue towards vs, may draw our loue towards thee, and that becauſe mercy is with thee, thou maieſt bee feared. Grant theſe things good Father, and all other needfull graces for our ſoules or bodies, or any of thine tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row out the whole world, for Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb facs="tcp:21561:104"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21561:104"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:21561:105"/> Chriſts ſake, in whoſe name we further call vpon thee as he hath taught vs in his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, ſaying; <hi>Our Father which art in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21561:105"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
